<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The proceedings of the General Assembly of the clergie of France assembled in the year 1682. at Paris, and in the year 1685. at S. Germains in Laye, concerning religion translated out of French into English by N.N.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55953</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831931</idno>
  <idno type="VID">36398</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240911196</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220535</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831931</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831931e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2054:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The proceedings of the General Assembly of the clergie of France assembled in the year 1682. at Paris, and in the year 1685. at S. Germains in Laye, concerning religion translated out of French into English by N.N.</title>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by I. Chrysostome Malte, at the good Pastor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Lille :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Below imprint: With priveledge.</note>
                  <note>Gathered in 2's.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Clergy --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36398:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF THE</hi> Clergie of France Assembled in the year <hi>1682.</hi> at Paris, and in the year <hi>1685.</hi> at S. Germains in Laye, <hi>CONCERNING RELIGION</hi> Translated out of French into English by <hi>N. N.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LILLE, Printed by I. CHRYSOSTOME MALTE, at the good Pastor, 1686.</hi> With Priveledge.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:36398:2"/>
            <p>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FUIMUS</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Right Hon.<seg rend="sup">ble</seg> Charles Viscount Bruce of Ampthill (Son and Heir Apparent of Thomas Earl of Ailesbury) and Baron Bruce of Whorlebon 1712</p>
                     <figDesc>bookplate</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:36398:2"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR TO THE READER,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hear present thee with à peece, which has but just learn'd to speak à litle broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken English, however as à stranger I doubt not of thy one goodnesse but thou wilt excuse the trips he makes hear &amp; there in his expression, and impute the faults which thou findest therin to the place that brought him forth, litle or no English being there spoaken, and the Printer à perfect stranger to our languadge, but as the designe was never to please thee with fine phrases, nor with Elegant speeches, so I intreat thee to accept therof, as intended purely to imforme thee in plaine termes with all the proceedings of the generall assembly of the Clergie of France lately assembled as thou wilt find by the severall dates &amp; times therin mentioned; &amp; wheras the french Hugonots that flock dayly into the Dominions of England and
<pb facs="tcp:36398:3"/> Ireland, on accompt of Religion, are not wanting to foment heats &amp; envey between the subjects of the one &amp; the other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, adding still (to make their case the more lamentable) new fuell to the old fire, it being à receaved maxime, that ill will, never speaks well; &amp; à story never loseth any thing by the carriadge; so I ludg'd for truth's sake, that 'twould be convenient to publish in our languadge the whole proceedings of the said Clergie of France against the Pretended Reformed, &amp; by so doeing to informe our litle English world, how farr the Clergie of France was concern'd in the persecution (as they call it) of the Hugonots.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the first place Courteous reader, I present thee vvith their proceedings in the assembly of</hi> 1682. <hi>at Paris, upon this point, under the title of</hi> A PASTORALL ADVERTISEMENT, <hi>by vvhich you vvill find, insteed of Crueltys, the most svveetest, the most tenderest, &amp; the most kindest Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to the Pretended Reformed for their reunion, that euer vvas, being vvithout doubt, the dictates of the holy Ghost; and is indeed all the Rigour, that the Clergie did excercise at that time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this fatherly aduise of the Clergie of France being mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>represented to the people of the P. R. R. by their Ministers infuseing into the minds of those under their tuition à fresh supply of their old leven of Calumnie &amp; scandall, interpreting, union to idolatry, peace to Paganissme, &amp; Reconciliation to Anti-Christ, with other Barbarous Reflections, persuadeing their pupils, that wee believe strange Doctrine and hold principals truly Pagan, imputeing à number of Errors unto us for faith which wee utterly Renounce &amp; Condemn; and to speake really I cannot blame the poore people (who know no better) to have à horrour against the Catholick faith, for on my conscience, if the Catholick Religion were such à bloody, Idolatrous &amp; abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Religion as they persuade the people it is, I would soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner choose to turne turk rather then Catholick, &amp; follow Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met rather then Anti-Christ, Esteemeing it salfer to receave the Alcaron, rather then adore stocks &amp; stones for Gods, as they with Impudence persuade the people wee do; by which means the Ignorant &amp; the libertine are à Gog, and for morning &amp; Evening
<pb facs="tcp:36398:3"/> service they have this, that the Papists are Idolaters, that they Rob God of his honnour, that they sett the Creature aboue the Creator, that wee surpass the Pagans for number &amp; sorts of Gods, nay our very hogs are infected with this Error, according to a harrangue which was held forth of late, I will not name the gentleman least à blush might Rise in his face, which would be more proper in his heart, by à true Repentance for that abuse not onely of himselfe &amp; his Auditory, but of the Catholicks his neighbours &amp; of the saints themselves, for whom he ought to have à Respect, in as much as they are the beloued of God &amp; are in glorie with the father which is in heaven, &amp; not by Rediculous Languadge unbecomeing à Prelat in the Pulpit, to affront hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, before the face of heaven &amp; Earth; who not content to Calumniate the saints by markeing them out for false Gods to men, but also to swine, as Saint ANTHONIE is there quoted to be the God of our pigs; oh! unchristian Expression, as un maner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly said, as disloyally spoaken, did he not know that JAMES the seacond our dread soveraign was of the same faith with us, and that saying the Catholicks do adore false Gods, is to say the KING is an Idolater, for to scandalize the faith of the Church of Rome, is to scandalize the KING who makes profession of that faith; to say the Pope is Anti-Christ, is to say the KING is à follower of Anti-Christ, &amp; he that scandalizeth the KING, is à scandall to the Church of England, which hath no head on earth but that KING whom they scandalize, &amp; unto whom the law doth give the keays of the Church of England in that statute, which makes the KING head of the Church, next and imediate under Christ, as well in spirituall as temporall, according to the express words of the act &amp; ten̄our of the oath of supremacie; but what do I speake of this, as if 'twas a new thing, for the KING &amp; Church to be scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized by such P—s, as calls Saint ANTHONY the God of our pigs: But to kennell that discourse with an other made not an age since by a gentleman of the same profession, whose whole ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon did nothing else but endeavour to prove that the Pope was Anti-Christ. Which in it selfe is so Ridicule, that far from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing
<pb facs="tcp:36398:4"/> the least ground in Scripture, he hath not so much as an act of Parliament it selfe to prove it by, &amp; therfore to be throwne out of dores, as being neither law nor Gospell: for the whole Bible mentions but of one Anti-Christ to come, and his Daies will be short. Mat. 24.22. <hi>And unlesse those Daies had been Shorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, no flesh should be saved, but for the Elect the daies shall be short'ned.</hi> And his power is to endure but three years &amp; a halfe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.5. <hi>and power was given it</hi> (the beast) <hi>to worke two &amp; forty months.</hi> Which is Just three years &amp; a halfe, agreeing with all the holy fathers who Interpreted, <hi>A time, times and halfe a time</hi> (so often mentioned in Daniel &amp; the Revelations) to be three years &amp; a halfe, a time one year, times two years &amp; halfe a time, to be hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe a year, according to the above text. But that Anti-Christ, who is to be against Christ, &amp; war against the Saints, should pray to Saints, &amp; Contribute with all his force to carrie on the war against enemies to the name of JESUS-CHRIST as the Pope &amp; his predecessors have done, or that wee were to have a Continuall succession of as many Anti-Christs as wee have had of Popes for above 1600. years, is what I find no authority for in the whole word of God.</p>
            <p>This digression courteous Reader, being a litle out of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent road, let's returne to what concernes the ensueing treatise; which as I told thee before, is the whole proceedings of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Assembly of the Clergie of France, against the Hugonots CONCERNING RELIGION. Except some few circular Letters, to all the Prelats of the Realme, the Catologue of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall books which they condemn'd &amp; some such proceedings which no ways concerns this purpose, all the Rest is exactly translated, as their advertisement to the Pretended Reformed, their speech to the king, their Complaint to the king, &amp; of what it was they did complaine, by which yow will find they did not in the least desire the king to disturb or molest the Excercise of the P. R. Religion, nor so much, as pray him to Revoke any Edict whatever which tollerated the Excercise of their Religion, for that there was no Edict which gave them the priveledge to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate
<pb facs="tcp:36398:4"/> the Catholik Church &amp; to impute erronius Doctrines unto us for faith, which wee utterly abominate and Condemn, &amp; that the said abuse might be Remedied for the future was all they desired, in order wherunto the KING sets forth an Edict to that Effect as thou wilt find in the end of the book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> 1682. <hi>They made their advertisement, &amp; on the</hi> 14th. <hi>of July</hi> 1685. <hi>They made their complaint to the KING; on the</hi> 21th. <hi>of July</hi> 1685. <hi>They made their speeeh to the KING in takeing leave of his Majestie, &amp; in August following the KING put forth his proclamation or Edict; but notwithstanding these proceedings of the Clergie &amp; the said Edict of the KING (although thousands were by the grace of God therby converted) yet the Ministers did never the less persevere &amp; Continue their Calumnies, even against the said Advertisement &amp; Edict, upon. Which the KING disatisfied, at their disobedience, did on the</hi> 22th. <hi>of October following set forth an Edict prohibiting the Excercise of the P. R. Religion through out his dominions, Comanding the Ministers of the said P. R. Religion, that would not be Reconciled to depart his KINGdome within fifteen dayes, therby Recaleing all his subjects of the P. R. Religion home within</hi> 4. <hi>months, &amp; forbiding any others of the said Religion to transport them selves or substance out of his Jurisdictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But as this Edict, is separate from the intent, which was onely to set forth how far the Clergie of France was Concern'd in the affaire of the Hugunots, &amp; their proceedings therupon &amp; no more, &amp; this Edict being the sole act of the KING no ways therunto solicited by the Clergie, &amp; in which they had no hand, I did not thinck my selfe oblidged to translate it, although I have given thee the breife contents therof. Comitting the whole to thy favourable Conjecture, shall abreviate, with desire &amp; Instance that where faults have Escaped (as nature is fraill) to atribute the same to the weaknesse of the translator &amp; omissions of the press, &amp; not to that vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable assembly of the Clergie of France Composed of so great a number of Prelats, famous through out the world for their piety &amp; learning; &amp; to the end their labours may have their Effect in thee gentle Reader, &amp; in all others who are devided from the unity of. Ephes:</hi> 4.5. One Faith <hi>without which the Apostle says 'tis imposible to please God, let us therefore dispose our selves in the</hi> Name of the Liveing God <hi>seriously to consider of
<pb facs="tcp:36398:5"/> union, &amp; insteed of cavilling disputes which creates heats &amp; aversions &amp; sets each party on the Rack of Invention how to widen the gap, let us I say, constantly &amp; without ceaseing with pure intention &amp; holy devotion pray, that God of his mercie may open the eyes of those that are out of the truth to see their Error, &amp; let every one who desires to be of the true flocke of Christ devoutly pray, that if he be not in the Right way of faith which leads to heaven, that God by his grace may force our wills to believe in his one truth through JESUS-CHRIST</hi> our lord, <hi>unto which dear Reader say Amen; with him that is, thy.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WELL WISHER &amp; SERVANT, N. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36398:5"/>
                  <head>A PASTORALL ADVERTISEMENT BY The Church of France Assembled at Paris by authority of the King; TO <hi>Those of the Pretended Reformed Religion for their Conversion, and Reconciliation, to the Catholick Church.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is à long time, Most dear Brethren, that the whole Church of Christ is lamenting for you, &amp; that this holy mother full of à Most holy &amp; Most sincere tenderness for her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, sees you with Extreame greife always à stray, as if you were lost in the frightfull solitude of Error, since by à wilfull schisme you seperated your selves from her Bosom, For as à true Mother how could she forget them she carried in her womb? or how could it be possible for this Church to thinck no more of you whom she loued so much, &amp; so well, that your unthanckfullness; hinders you not from being of the number of her infants unto whom the poison of heresie has made odious,
<pb facs="tcp:36398:6"/> the Catholick truths, &amp; that the tempest occasion'd by the Revolt of Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisme has made forsake her holy &amp; ancient doctrine of the true faith, snatching you unhappily from the center &amp; head of Christian unity.</p>
                  <p>Behold, most dear Brethren, the subject of her tears, she complains bitterly, this desolated Mother, of this, that haveing mistaken the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness that she has for yow, yow have rent her bowells. She searches, she seeks, for you her stray'd Children, she recalls you as the Patridge doth her litle ones, she strives &amp; forceth her selfe to gather yow under her wings, as the hen doth her chickins, she solicites yow, she intreats yow, she prays yow, to take your way to heaven as the Eagle doth her young; always pierced with liveing pains of à painfull labour, she endeavours, weak Infants, to regaine your love à seacond time, fully Resolued for this Effect to suffer all sorts of torments, untill that shee sees JESUS-CHRIST truly Rissen &amp; renewed in your hearts.</p>
                  <p>'Tis in this prospect, that wee Archbishops, Bishops, &amp; others deputed of the Clergie of France, whom the holy Ghost has Established for to governe the Church in which yow were brought forth, &amp; who by a perpetuall suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession, holds to this day the same faith, &amp; occupie the same seats as the holy Prelats did, who brought the Christian Religion amongst our Gaules, come to seek yow; &amp; by the function which wee Exercice of Ambassadors for JESUS-CHRIST, as if God himselfe by our mouth spake unto yow, wee exhort yow, and wee summon yow to tell us <hi>wherfore have you se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated your selves from us?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the present state yow now are in, owne it, or owne it not, yow are in Effect our Brethren, honoured heartofore by our common father which is in heaven, with the title of his adopted, &amp; brought up by the same mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is the Church, in hopes to possess one day the inheritance de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd for her true Children.</p>
                  <p>And he himselfe that dared to seduce yow by his Error, &amp; that perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded yow to obey the truth no more, the head of your pretended Reforme, did he not live with us before his schisme as our Brother? did he not dwell in the same house of our father? did he not eat of the same spirituall food? did he not with us do the same offices, &amp; acquit the same dutys of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Brother hood? Justifie, if you can before God your father, before the Church your Mother, before Catholicks your Brothers, the shame &amp; Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie
<pb facs="tcp:36398:6"/> of a separation so criminall, so violent &amp; so immoderate? do you Iustifie your selves of being devided from the body of JESUS-CHRIST; of being Retrench'd from the participation of the Sacraments of JESUS-CHRIST; of haveing made à cruell warr against the members of JESUS-CHRIST; of haveing vomited so much venome against the spouse of JESUS-CHRIST; &amp; of haveing renounced to the promises of JESUS-CHRIST; Excuse this fault &amp; wash of this spott if you can; &amp; because you can never do it, confess that this Oracle of the scripture falls directly upon you; <hi>The Revolted Child says boldly his Conduct is Iust; but when one asks him wherfore he for sooke the house of his father, he cannot Justifie his goeing forth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherfore Then, most dear Brethren, did yow not Remaine fixed to the root &amp; center of the Church with the Rest of the houshold? hovv comes it that yow over threw the alters, &amp; that in over throwing them, yow have broke the vou's and desires of all the faithfull? why did yow cut of the way of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers which lead unto heaven? since 'twas from the feet of these Alters, the voices of Christians were elevated even to the throne of God; why then fearing that they should cōtinue sendeing the accustomed prayers to heaven have yow broaken downe this misterious lather, in overthrowing by your Sacrilegious hands, those sacred prayers which served as the basis &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation therof; all other Sectaries that were before yow, were contented to Raise Alter against Alter; but yow, by an Enterprise of which the world did ignore untill your days, for to abolish entirely the Sacrifice of JESUS-CHRIST; yow have presum'd to demolish the Alters of the Lord of virtues where JESUS-CHRIST, the true shepheard, according to S. Augustin had chose his abode, &amp; where the true doue, which according to the same father is the Church, had built her nest for the security &amp; preservation of her litle ones.</p>
                  <p>But vvee vvill, that all this exces of vvhich vvee have spoke; &amp; Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally all that has happen'd since your Revolt; vvhether of vvars against the Church, or of Errors against the Doctrine, has been the Effect of that furie vvhich ordinarily accompagnies all sorts of schismes; &amp; that it ought rather to be atributed to the evill spirit of Revolt, then to any vvicked inclination of your parte; the Continuall &amp; cheife complaint vvhich at all times vvee make against you, &amp; upon vvich vvee at present
<pb facs="tcp:36398:7"/> insist, is againe &amp; allvvays to demand of you, <hi>Why did yow separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te your selves from us?</hi> So long as you do not ansvver precisely to this question; vvhatever you may say or vvrite upon all other subjects, vvill be to no purpose.</p>
                  <p>Wee doubt not, but you vvill hear appply the old ansvver so familiar to all schismaticks; &amp; knovving by Experience that 'tis impossible for you to shake the foundation of our beliefe, you vvill have recours to the spetious pretext of the disordered lives of severall people of our Religion; &amp; that you vvil alleadge, that makeing profession to lead à life vvholy Reform'd &amp; to follovv the most strict rules of Christianity, it vvas not beseeming your Reputations, nor salfe for your consciences, to Remain any longer amongst people of so Reproachfull behaviour? vvas this then, Most dear Brethren, the only motiff for vvhich yovv Iudg'd it lavvfull to breake the holy unity of Christianity, to Blaspheme against the heritadge of your Brethren, to Scoff at the truth &amp; efficacie of the holy Sacraments of the church? Behold to vvhat à degree you are Remoued from the spirit of the Gospell: it's Certaine that if all th se crimes vvhich you object, vvere vvithout doubt, as perhaps not so many, &amp; of less vveight, or perhaps vvere hidden, or altogether invented or Imaginarie, or grant that they vvere all reall, publick &amp; aver'd, and that they vvere greater &amp; vvorss then you say, yet good Christians ought to spare the cockle that grovvs amongst the vvheat in Consideration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the good corne; because vvee are bound to beare vvith the frailties of our Brethren, to preserve comunion vvith the Just. <hi>Moses, had he recours to schisme, when so many thousands of men murmur'd against God; Samuell, had he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours to schisme, when the sons of Hely &amp;c. comitted such un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy sacriledge; JESUS-CHRIST, had he recours to schisme, when he was sold to his enemies by Judas the theife, divill, &amp; traitor; The Apostles, did they fall into schisme with their false Brethren &amp; false Apostles enemies of them, and of their Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne? &amp; Saint Paul who made it his businesse to forget his proper intrests, for the sake of those of JESUS-CHRIST, did he not always abide with an Extreame patience, amongst those who sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed the interests of JESUS-CHRIST to their unhappy lusts;</hi> &amp; you, our most dear Brethren, you have not onely resolved not to
<pb facs="tcp:36398:7"/> bear with the pretended defects of your Mother the Church &amp; spouse of JESUS-CHRIST; but you must absent your selves from her comunion, dishonouring &amp; disgraceing her throughout the whole world; &amp; that you might Rent &amp; divide her with the more Cruelty, yow have accused her of Blemishes vvherof she vvas vvholy innocent, &amp; to be found onely in some fevv particular persons, not Considering that JESUS-CHRIST, hath cleans'd her in the pure vvaters of his Baptisme by the vvord of life, to the end Ephes. <hi>5.27. That he might present it to himselfe a glorious Church, not haveing spot, or wrinckle, or any such thing, but that it Should be holy &amp; without Blemish.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What is it novv, that Remains for us, most dear Brethren, if it be not to apply unto you the Councill of the holy Ghost: <hi>Math. 5.9. Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed are the Peace-makers; for they shall be caled the children of God, and to conjure you by those bowells which you have rent; by the bosome of your dear Mother the Church, which you have forsaken; by the Brotherly love, which you have so often viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; by the Sacraments of JESUS-CHRIST which you have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalved; by the Alters of the liveing God, which you have overthrowne; &amp; finally by all that's most sacred &amp; holy, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven &amp; Earth, seriously to thinck of your amendment, of your returne &amp; of your reconciliation with your Mother the Church, &amp; what can there now Remaine for you, but to forget forever the schisme into which you are falen; to remember the infinite tendernesses of the Church which loves you so well, &amp; out of hand to Returne to the house of your father; where mercenaries themselves do live in plenty, whilst you, stray'd by your Revolte into a desolate country without habitation, without pathes &amp; without waters, find not so much as the least crum to sustaine you, in your languishment, against the spirituall hunger which Consumes &amp; devoures you; why do you delay, &amp; how comes it that you still Resist; is it that you are ashamed to Re-assume the qualitie of being sonns of the Church, whilst LOUIS THE GREAT; her Eldest son makes it his cheife glorie to raise dayly new tropheis to the honnour of à Mother so worthy; his happiness finds no limits but by your obstinacy only; seeing him
<pb facs="tcp:36398:8"/> Erect dayly so many pious &amp; holy Monuments to the advantadge of Christianity; the only thing that can be à troble to him, is to see such à number of his subjects, such enemies of his Religion &amp; desertors of the Antient Christian Army, who not content to have broken downe the Alters of their fore fathers, to abandon themselves to an unknowne worship &amp; to strange ceremonies, are still obstinate to Remaine in their first Errors this Great prince of late Exprest himselfe unto us, upon the desire he had for your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, after à manner which of it selfe would be suffitient to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit him the name of most Christian, when he protested unto us, that he desired your Reunion to the Church with so great à heart, that he would Esteem himselfe happy to Contribute of his one blood, &amp; with loss of his invincible Arme, with which he has subdved such numbers of his Enemies &amp; gain'd such vast con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests. Oh, why then most dear Brethren, will you any longer hinder your King, after haveing vanquisht such dreadfull forces, taken so many stong places, subjected such great Provinces, &amp; heap'd triumph upon triumph, to gather now this last palme which he Esteemes more then all the Rest</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, most dear Brethren when wee conjure you with so much Instance &amp; that vvee Exhort you so tenderly, to give ear to the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells of peace &amp; of Reconciliation which wee give unto you; do not dear Brethren answer us &amp; say: WHERFORE DO YOU SEEK VS? this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie is the Languadge of that obstinacy which Retains you in the schis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; &amp; not of Charity which makes Christians &amp; Reunites them in one &amp; the same society. Remember your selves that in seeking you wee do execute the order &amp; will of the spirit of truth &amp; of peace, who comands us by his prophete, to call upon those without ceaseing, who would not have us call them Brethren: YOU ARE OVR BRETHREN.</p>
                  <p>Oh, was there ever à time more proper to recall yow to the comu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Rome then this in which the Church is governed by the Pope INNOCENT the XI. whose life &amp; manners formed upon the most an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient &amp; most severe rules of Christian discipline, makes apparent to the world in our days, a Modele of sanctity the most perfect? in such
<pb facs="tcp:36398:8"/> sort, that you can never do any thing for your greater glorie, nor of more profit for your salvation then to reconcile your selves with this holy Pope, whose life is a schoole of all liveing virtues &amp; perfections.</p>
                  <p>You then, poore diseased, who stand in such need of à Phisitian; you, members of JESUS-CHRIST, considerable to the truth; because you were redeem'd with the same blood as wee were; but unhappily seperated from the head &amp; members of the Church by the dreadfull artifices of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemie; permitt that the immortall hand of God may make you whole. Receave with one spirit and with one heart this fatherly advise, or if you pleas this instant pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r; for such is our tendernesse &amp; compassion for yow that wee thought fit to invite you after this manner. R'enter then, our most dear Brethren, by this favourable gate which Brotherly love hath open'd unto you in the be halfe of the Church; to the end that by the helpe of the all powerfull God, the thick clouds of your Errors being on'st dissipated, the light of truth may more &amp; more manifest it selfe in you. Be not the occasion of the losse of so many poore souls, by the false Ideas of our belife, with which you wholy possess them who otherwise would find their saluatiō with the flock of JESUS-CHRIST; do not Imagin that it is à shame to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer your paine to him that can cure you. Suffer your selues to be touched with Repentence, &amp; do not any longer Refuse those Remedies which can restore you to health. For at last you must be persuaded, that of all things which à Christian can do, the most glorious, &amp; that which one may say, is onely necessarie, is to acknowledge his Error before God.</p>
                  <p>Which if you resuse to do, after so pressing Exhortations of our part; &amp; if you will not, nor admitt your selves to be ouercome by our prayers, nor gain'd by our tender loue, nor submitt to our advice, know that the Angels of peace will weep bitterly; yet notwithstanding wee wil neuer Abandon you to your selves the more for that, although wee have to do vvith à stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born &amp; stiff necked people; yet wee will still seeke in you the lambs of JESUS-CHRIST through the thornes and Bryars vvhich hinders your Reunion vvith his flock, &amp; after vvee haue done our endeavours vvith you, &amp; by you rejected, to Inspire you vvith the thoughts of peace, by offerring you these ready vvays of Reconciliation vvith the Church; the grace of peace vvhich vvee haue offerred unto you vvith so much sincerity &amp; tenderness vvill return unto uss after being cast out by you, &amp; God vvill not farther
<pb facs="tcp:36398:9"/> aske nor call us to an accoumpt for your souls. &amp; because that this last Error vvill be more Criminell in yovv then all the formers, you cannot but expect euills to fall upon you Incomparably more dreadfull then all that ever your Reuolt &amp; schisme has brought upon you to this day. But vvee hope &amp; expect from you our most dear Brethren better Resolutions, and more fauourable designs for your salvation. Given at Paris in the generall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Clergie of France the first day of July &amp; year of grace <hi>1682.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>† <hi>Francis, Archbishop of Paris, President.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Charles M. le Tellier, Archbishop of Reims.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Charles, Archbishop of Ambrun.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>James, Archbishop &amp; Duke of Cambray.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Hiacynthe, Archbishop of Alby.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Mi. Phelypeaux, P. P. Archbishop of Bourges.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>James Nic. Colbert, Archbishop of Carthage Coadjutor of Rouen.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Louis de Bourlemont, Archbishop of Bourdeaux.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Gilbert, Bishop of Tournay.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Nicholas, Bishop of Riez.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Daniell de Cosnac, Bishop &amp; Comte of Valence &amp; Die.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Gabriell, Bishop of Autun.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>William Bishop of Basas.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Gabriell Ph. de Froullay de Tesse, Bishop of Auranches.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>James Benigne, Bishop of Meaux.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Sebastian du Guemadeuc, Bishop of S. Malo.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>L. M. Ar. de Simiane de Gordes, Bishop &amp; Duke of Langres.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Fr. Leon, Bishop of Glandeves.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Lucas, Bishop of Frejus.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>J. B. M. Colbert, Bishop &amp; Duke of Montauban.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Charles de Pradell, Bishop of Montpellier.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Fra. Placide Bishop of Mande.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Charles, Bishop of Lavaur.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Andrew, Bishop of</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Francis, Bishop of Troyes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>L. Ant. Bishop &amp; Count of Chalons.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:36398:9"/>
                           <item>† <hi>Francis Ig. Bishop of Treguier.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Peter, Bishop of Belley.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Gabriell Bishop of Gonferans.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Louis Alphonse, Bishop of Alet.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>Humbert, Bishop of Tulles.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>† <hi>J. B. d'Estampes, Bishop of Marseille.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Fran. de Camps, named coadjutor of Glandeve.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Saint Georges, named to the Bishoprick of Mascon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Paulus Phil. de Lusignan.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Lud. d'Espinay de S. Leu.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cocquelin.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Lambert.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>P. de Bermond.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A. H. de Fleury.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Viens.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>F. Feu.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A. de Maupeon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Le Franc de la Grange.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Senaux.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Parra, Dean of Belley.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Boche.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>M. de Ratabon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Clemens de Poudeux.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Bigot.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Fourges.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Villeneve de Vence.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>C. Leny de Coadelets.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>La Faye.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Pierre le Roy.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>I. F. de l'Escure.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A. de Soupets.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A. Argoud Dean of Vienne.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gerbais.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Bausset.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>G. Bochart de Champigny.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <pb facs="tcp:36398:10"/>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Courcier.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cherron.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A Faure.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>F. Maucroix.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De la Borey.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>De Franqueville.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Armandus Bazinde Bessons, Agent Generall of the Clregie.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Desmarets Agent Generall of the Clergie.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36398:10"/>
                  <p>A SPEECH MADE TO THE MOST-CHRISTIAN KING, At Versailles the 21. of July 1685.</p>
                  <p>BY <hi>The most Jllustrious and most</hi> REVEREND LORD JAMES NICOLAS COLBERT, <hi>Archbishop &amp; Primate of Carthagé, &amp; Coajutor of Rouen. assisted by the Lords, Archbishops, Bishops, and others deputed of the generall Assembly, of the Clergie of France, held at S. Germains in Laye, in the said year, in taking leaue of his Majestie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>TOGETHER With several Edicts of the King, and other passages of the Clergie of France, in the said Generall Assembly concerning Religion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Translated out of French into English by N. N.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At LILLE, Printed by, J. CHRYSOSTOME MALTE, at the good Pastor, 1686. <hi>With Priveledge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="speech">
                  <pb facs="tcp:36398:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36398:11"/>
                  <head>TO THE KING:</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>REAT SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE CLERGIE of France, that formerly approach'd not their Soveraigns, but to set forth the dolefull Jmages of an opprest &amp; sighing Church; comes this day acknowledgeing the Joyes of their hearts demonstrateing to your Majestie, the same Church surrounded with the glorie she holds of your piety.</p>
                  <p>She has appear'd for above an age, on the brinks of her Ruine; her bowells Rent by her one Children, betray'd by those that ought to support and defend her, and made à prey to her most cruell ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; but after à long &amp; languishing oppression, she Respir'd à litle before your glorious birth; for with you she began to live, with you she mounted the throne, and the years of her encrease, she reckons by the years of your Reigne; &amp; 'tis under the most flouris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing Empire of the world wee see her this day more flourishing then ever.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:36398:12"/>
                  <p>If yet she remembers her trobles and miseries past, 'tis but the better to Relish the perfect happiness you make her enjoye; she is now free from agitation or fear under the wings of your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; she is also (if I dare Express it) without desires, since your zelé leaves her no time to Consider, and that your goodnesse so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten surpasseth her wishes.</p>
                  <p>This ardent zelé for the faith, this fatherly goodness in all the affairs of the Church (qualities most rare in Princes) occasions GREAT SIR, the true subject of our Elogies. Wee leave your other subjects to admire the abundance of other virtues in you; some will Represent you as à well-doeing Monarch, liberall, magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, true to his promiss, firme and inflexible against all sorts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice, upright and equitable, even to give sentencé against his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per intrests; à truly-great master of his people, but à greater master of himselfe; others will Respect you as à King always wise, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes victorious, whose impenetrable design's are sooner execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then knowne; who Reigns not onely over his subjects by his soveraigne Authority, but over his councill by the superiority of his genius, and over the courts of his neighbours, by the penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his witt, &amp; his wisdome in which he is able to Instruct his ministers; who knows by himselfe to surpass the greatest of men, and without them, Resolue, undertake and Execute; who gives laws, as well by sea, as by land; who launceth when he pleaseth, his thunder, even to the borders of Afrique; who knows to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proud nations, and reduce their soveraigns to come to the feet of his throné, acknowledging his power and imploreing his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie.</p>
                  <p>Your enemies them selves SIR, cannot forbear to praise your heroick actions, they are forc't to Confess, that nothing is able to Resist you; the merrit of the conquerour sweetening in some sorte the misfortune of the Conquered.</p>
                  <p>'Tis not for us GREAT SIR, to speake the Astonsihing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress of your triumphing armes, wee ought not to mixt à shineing vallour, that is but the object of admiration to men, with those holy actions Esteem'd by heaven: the Clergie SIR, Joynes in the whole
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36398:12"/> to Rejoyce in your piety, which is always attentive to the Intrests of the church, and omitts nothing that can be necessarie to Rebuild those walls that have been demolished, to the end, her extent may reach even beyond the seas, to places where she is not knowne, as it were, to make her triumph, both in the one, &amp; the other, world.</p>
                  <p>But what do I say? the Church of her selfe ought she not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate those victories, which you have so hapily apply'd to the propagation of the faith, and the extinction of heresie? it seems that you have onely fought &amp; triumph'd but for GOD; and the fruit you gather by the peace, gives us to understand, what was the principall end of your conquests; and 'tis by those victories that you have Establish't this unquestionable power, which holds from hence-forth your neighbours by the Reines, and taketh from the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks of your kingdomes the Impudence to Rebell &amp; hopes to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seed by seditious Intrigues with the enemies of your state.</p>
                  <p>Had it been ambition, that moved you to arme; unto where, might you not have extended your empire? &amp; do wee not knowe; that your being in haste to end the warr, even when the greatest of advantages was in your power, that 'twas nothing els, but the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presment you had to give your whole cares, to the progress of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Conversion of so many souls engadged in Error, which of all other conquests seem'd to you the most glorious, and the triumph the most-worthy, of à King the most Christian.</p>
                  <p>But great as your puissance was, she still wanted the aide of your Goodness in winning the hearts of your Subjects in Heresie misledd, who now prostrate the obstinacie of their Spirits, to the Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of your will, seeing by good works you combate the hardness of their hearts? and perhaps they could never have entred into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some of the Church, by any, other way then by that path spred with flowers which you have opened unto them.</p>
                  <p>It must also GREAT SIR, be acknowledged, that what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trest wee have in the extirpation of heresie, is transported by our Joy, some thing aboue the greife wee should have, if to surmount this cloud à vexatious necessity should force your zelé, to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to fier and sword, as in precedeing Reigns your Royall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36398:13"/> have been forced to do. Wee should take parte in à holy &amp; Just warr, and wee should also abhor it, because 'twould be cruell and sanguine; wee would offer our vow's for the sucsess of your sacred armes; but could not behold without trembling the dreadfull exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, of which the God of Revenge would make you the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument; however wee would mixt our voices with the publique acclamations of your victories, and in secret should lament on à triumph, that with the defeat of our enemies would be enwrap'd the loss of our brethren.</p>
                  <p>This day then, seeing you combate the pride of Heresie, but by sweetness, and discreetness of government; that your laws are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by good-deeds your onely armes; and that the advantadges you bring, are of dammadge to none but to the Demon of Revolt &amp; of Schisme; wee have but the pure acts of thancks-giveings to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto heaven, that inspired you, to these meeke &amp; prudent means to vanquish all Error, and to be able by mingling à litle severity with abundance of graces &amp; favours, to re-unite to the Church, those that are found to have been unhappily separated.</p>
                  <p>Wee confess GREAT SIR, that 'tis to your Majestie alone, wee shall soone owe the Intire r'establishment of the faith of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; must it not alsoe be, that the state is already indebted to you, for her salfty &amp; glory; the church owes, her victorie and triumph to none but to you; or otherwise to your Reign, which heaven would have to be à Reign of wonders, or elss its most fairest orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had been wanting; it may be well said one day of your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, what the Scriptures says of Divers great kings of Judea: he has Reduced his enemies &amp; advanced the Monarchie, he has authorised and Reformed the laws, &amp; has made Justice reign, but to them was added, the reproach which the holy ghost gave those Princes, they did not abolish the sacrafices to Idolls that was done on the tops of the mountains.</p>
                  <p>That your name GREAT SIR, may be à stranger to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, is what your zele has already done, which posterity will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard as the source of your prosperities, and the top of your glories.</p>
                  <p>'Twas not onely the r'establishment of churches and Alters, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36398:13"/> transported your zelé, but the undertakeing to revive devotion and good maners, forwhich your Majestie has labour'd with sucsess, as well by your example as by your orders.</p>
                  <p>'Tis now à day's honourable to practise virtues, and if vice be not altogether destroy'd, she is reduced at least to be hidd, and the vails that covers her, spares to good people à displeaseing scandale, and saves weake souls from perill &amp; dreadfull Contagion.</p>
                  <p>Let's thinck no more of those days of darkness, when the greatest part of them that remain'd in the bosome of the Church, seemingly were not, but for outrage the most sencible, when blasphemies, and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crelegious scoffing at all that was sacred, so impudently was boasted, by monsters of Infidelity who now disapear under your Happy Reign, and if the Remonstrances, so often reiterated upon this Subiect, do not give us suffitient kowledge of those disorders, wee shall Ignore them for ever. what's become of that other Monster produc'd by the spirit of Revenge, that was always besmer'd with the blood of men, but most of all with the blood of the french nobility; wee have but to leave it in Eternal oblivion, where long since you have plac'd it; you have vtterly stifled it, so mighty as it appear'd: you well knew, to overthrow base maxims of honour and shame; and by how much more detestable errour had given falls honour to Revenge, by so much the more Jgnomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious will it be, not to obey you; and thus your will alone has overuled an inveterate custome of wickedness, and the cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall inclinations of men.</p>
                  <p>The Clergie disposes them selves now, onely to be as spectators, to behold the end of all your holy undertakeings, after haveing admired so glorious à begining; she ceases to use Remonstrances, if there may be occasion, it suficeth that you know it; in this Assembly she comes to acknowledge the signall Effects of your Royall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, perswaded that you have design'd her à long continuance of graces &amp; favours, in these and other times, with those circumstances, which you alone know so well to accompagnie; she would fear by demands to disturb, the order your wisdome has establish't, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to put limits, where your zelé had plac'd none.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36398:14"/>
                  <p>The onely affair that takes us up, is the obligation to render to your Majesty our most humble acknowledgements; and after so Just à duty, assur'd that wee are in your powerfull protection, shall seperate our selves without the least disquiet, and goe into the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall provinces of your Realme, to offer the praises due, by the Church to your zelé, where every shepherd will reioyce to see, the number of his flock encreas'd by your cares, for which every of us will redouble his voice, to obteine from heaven, that God may redouble his blessings in favour of à Prince, that acquires them by actions so glorious, &amp; to Religion so usefull.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="complaint">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36398:14"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE COMPLAINT.</hi> Of the generall Assembly of the Clergie of France, against the Invective Calumnies, base Injuries, &amp; falsities, which the Pretended Reformers have spread, and dayly publish in their boocks and Preachings, à gainst the Doctrine of the holy Catholique Church, Carried to the King by the body of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie the 14th day of July 1685.</head>
                  <head type="sub">TO THE KING.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE CLERGIE of your Realme, has made severall complaints to your Majesty against those of the pretended Reformed Religion,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36398:15"/> with great precaution, to include any thing but what was most needfull, and that could be most clearly proved.</p>
                  <p>But espetially she thought it her duty, to separate this one, from all the rest, it being the onely thing that grieves her above all, &amp; that seems to her the most important, which she grounds upon proofs the most evident.</p>
                  <p>This complaint GREAT SIR; concerns the faith of the holy Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que church, whose purity, the ministers and writers of the pretended Reformed Religion, endeavours to blacken, by most cruell Injuries, &amp; by most falss &amp; scandelous Calumnies.</p>
                  <p>They knew they could not attaque her by solid reason, for they found by experience, that the arguments, which they made use of when they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke, to prove their new Doctrine, made but à very weake impression on the minds of the people, they see dayly, that when they faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the true sence of the Catholique Church, that then they are not able, to Justifie their separation, nor excuse the excess of the first authors of their sect; and being unable to defend themselves by these means, they have recourse to a most uniust and pernitious invention, to impute to the Catholique Church an infinite number of most gros, and insufferable errors: they sopose she dissembles, or that she condemns the most essentiall truths of Religion; and represents her, under the most frightfull figure of à Church professing damnable and idolatrous doctrines, that believes not the vereties of true faith, and 'tis no wonder, they should by these means, infuse hatred, aversion &amp; horrour of the Church, into the mindes of the people that are under their tuition.</p>
                  <p>The Clergie with greife long since beheld the dreadfull Effects of this distemper, and sought means to put a stop to it's cource.</p>
                  <p>In the last assembly of <hi>1682.</hi> she sett forth à fatherly advertissement to the pretended Reformers upon this subject, believeing, that by pressing them to explaine the Reasons of their separation, that they would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into themselues, and be ashamed to see, that it was grounded but upon sopositions and calumnies; &amp; thancks be to God, that attempt was not altogether fruitless, seeing, since that time the numbers almost infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of hereticks, that have been converted, there being but very few, that cannot but submitt themselves to this invincible argument; that as they can never have à just cause for separation, so all that the pretended Reformers aleadge, cannot have the least solidity.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:36398:15"/>
                  <p>But there is one obstacle that hinder'd, and that doth still hinder &amp; put à stop to the fruit, the most considerable that was hoped for, which is, that the voice of the Bishops, and Pastors of the Catholique Church could not reach the ears of the common people of the pretended Reformed Religion; their Ministers haveing either diverted them from readeing the said advertissement, or gave them a falss explication therof, as they do of the sacred scriptures and works of the holy fathers; by which means SIR, the greatest part of your subjects of the pretended Reformed Religion, are detain'd in their Errors; and the distemper is without cure, if your Majestie do not assist by your protection, and support by your Authority what the Clergie has so happily began.</p>
                  <p>Notwithstanding, the Kings your Majesties Royall predecessors, did not permit the Excercise of the pretended Reformed Religion, but upon consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the troblesomness of those times, and for other Reasons, now out of dores; and that in the flourishing state, wherin your val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour &amp; wisdome has plac'd your kingdome, the Clergie has most just cause to desire the revocation of those Edicts which conteins that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, is at present, not the point, on which the Clergie insists.</p>
                  <p>The Request, the Clergie most humbly makes to your Majesty, is not for the Revocation of any Edict whatever; for there is none, neither can their be any that permitts the pretended reformers, to Calumniate and belie the Catholique Church, and atribute unto her falss doctrines, which she teacheth not, &amp; which she never did believe or teach.</p>
                  <p>If fuch à liberty were, 'twould be a most unhappy priveledge, of which the ministers themselves ought to be ashamed.</p>
                  <p>Falss sopositions, detractions &amp; Calumnies, are crimes Condemn'd by all the laws of God and man; and are punish'd with severity, although they should touch but the Reputation of some particular person, and are yet more punishable, when they are given to attaint the intire body of the state.</p>
                  <p>How blind soever the pretended Reformers may be, it cannot reach to that degree, as to dare maintaine, that such crimes and the practise of them ought to be permitted, or so much as to complaine of what your Majesty shall prohibit them to comitt.</p>
                  <p>It's notwithstanding GREAT SIR, the onely favour, the Clergie begs of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36398:16"/> you, that dureing the time it shall please your Majesty to permitt, to the pretended Reformers, the Excercise of their Religion, that they may be defended from presumeing to continue the lies &amp; Calumnies they have usvally spred, &amp; which they dayly publish in their preachings and writeings.</p>
                  <p>Your Majesty will plainly see, that 'tis not without cause, the Clergie makes you this complaint.</p>
                  <p>Yet wee have forbore to Report divers of their expressions, which sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes all the order of modesty, &amp; that Saint Paul forbids the faithfull to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce; your Majesty will have horrour, to see <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Incredible excess, to which the passion of the pretended reformers have transported them.</p>
                  <p>There is not an article of our faith, against which they have not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted outrage, by most gross &amp; Insufferable Calumnies.</p>
                  <p>The Collection wherof, which the Clergie has made and which she takes the liberty to present to your Majesty, is the conviction.</p>
                  <p>They accuse the Catholique Church of professing Errors they accuse us, of not believing, the fundamentall verities of Christianity; &amp; to express their accusations, they serve themselves with expressions the most Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently uncivill in the world.</p>
                  <p>The Clergie, SIR, complains, of à maner of proceeding the most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable that ever was, and to shew plainly the Injustice, they humbly intreat your Majesty to compare the doctrine, which the Calvinists atri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Chruch of Rome, with that, which is contein'd in her profession of faith, and in the decissions of the holy Council of Trent.</p>
                  <p>This comparison is the most naturall &amp; most sure way to Judge of the Justice, or injustice of the pretended Reformers accusations; and is onely what the Clergie desires, with Respect to your Majesty.</p>
                  <p>Wee have set downe each article of faith in particular to avoid Confusion, and for the greater clearing of the truth; and in the same designe, wee have made to each article of faith two Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum's.</p>
                  <p>In the first wee have writt the express termes of the profession of faith &amp; decissions of the holy councill of Trent; and there your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty will see the true doctrine of the Catholique Church.</p>
                  <p>In the seacond wee have set forth the express words of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36398:16"/> Reformers in their boocks, where they expose the faith of the Church of Rome, and your Majesty will see what doctrine it is, that they impute unto us.</p>
                  <p>And by this paralell alone (then which there can be nothing more Inocent, and more sincere) your Majesty will clearly see, that they have no Resemblance to each other, but to the Contrary the differrence being so sencible &amp; palpable, between the doctrine which the Church of Rome professeth, and that which the pretended Reformers do attribute to her, that they are manifestly convicted of base impostures and Calumnies.</p>
                  <p>If the question were but of our particular persons, wee should never appear, to bring our complaints to your Majesty, for to obteine your Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and power for the Reparation of the Injuries that the Ministers day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give out of us in their libells; to the contrary, the Clergie would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, if they could wittness, by their patience and voluntarie forgiveing (the outrages they do) the sincere Charity they have for them, but wee cannot neglect the honnour of our Mother the Church, which the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters attacques, by their Calumnies, nor the conversion &amp; salvation of so great à number of souls which they Retaine in Errour by their false positions.</p>
                  <p>Wee doubt not SIR, by the same Considerations, but your Majesty will be most sencible who upon all occasions has shewn so much zele, for the salvation of your subjects, &amp; so much respect and veneration for the Church, but you will also Repress by your authority, an Injustice so wicked, and so contrary, not onely to the principles of Christianity, but even to the Common rules of naturall Right.</p>
                  <p>These things GREAT SIR, considered, wee most humbly pray your Majesty first, to renew by such means as your Majesty shall please &amp; Judge most convenient, such Edicts &amp; Declarations, by which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reformers are order'd to speake with Respect, of the Misteries of our Religion, and to forbid them when they have à mind to propound or refute any articles of our faith, any more to make use of such Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; unchristian Expressions, as hetherto they have done, &amp; which the Clergie has Collected, nor for the future to substitute the like. Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as the doctrine of the Catholique Church is clearly laid downe in her profession of faith, &amp; in the decissions of the holy councill of Trent,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36398:17"/> likewise to forbid them, to impute to the catholique Church, any other pretended Errors, as to this present they have had the Impudence to do, notwithstanding the Church has always detested and condemn'd them, in what authors soever such principles were found.</p>
                  <p>Yow will by this conduct GREAT SIR, imprint in the souls of all your subjects the Inviolable Respect they ought to have for Church and faith; and untill those of the pretended Reformed Religion shall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, they will the more freely submitt themselves to the orders of the Church, &amp; with better inclination will follow her doctrine, whilst the enemies of her truth &amp; glorie have not, at least the licence much longer to insuit, by their scandalous comportments.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>NAMES</hi> OF THE CLERGIE ASSEMBLED.</head>
                     <item>† <hi>FRANCIS Archbishop of Paris President.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>J. de MONTPEZAT Archbishop of Sens.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>De GRIGNAN Coadjutor of Arles.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>TH. de MONTPEZAT Archbishop of Tolose.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>HIACINTHE Archbishop of Alby.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>MI. de PHELYPEAUX, PP. Archbishop of Bourges.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>JAMES NICOLAS, Archbishop of Carthage, coadjutor of Rouen.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>LEWIS Archbishop of Bourdeaux.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>SUZE, named to the Archbishoprick of Auch.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>FRANCIS, Bishop of Amiens.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>DANIELL de COSNAC, Bishop &amp; Count of Valence &amp; die.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>FR. de COETLOGON, Bishop of Quimper.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>LEWIS Bishop of Mans.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:36398:17"/>
                     <item>† <hi>EFF. de CHAMBONAS, Bishop of Lod'eue.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>JOHN, Bishop of Ap't.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>LEWIS, Bishop of Sisteron.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>J. de MATIGNON Bishop of Condom.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>LEWIS, Bishop &amp; Count of Saint Paul.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>HENRY, Bishop &amp; Count of Chàlons.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>LEONARD, Bishop and Count of Lisieux.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>F. Bishop of Saint Papoul.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>FR. Bishop of Mande.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>FR. Bishop of Digne.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>MICHAELL, Bishop of Macon.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>FR. BOUTHILLIER, Bishop of Troyes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>GRIGNAN, Bishop of Carcassonne.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>CLAUDE, Bishop of Bouloigne.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>DOM. Bishop of l'Escar.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>FRANCIS THEOD. Bishop of Vence.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>† <hi>De Saint GEORGES, named Bishop of Clermont.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fr. Mallet de Graville de Drubec.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peter Armand de la Croye de Castries.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Henry du Faur de Pibrac.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De Valavoir.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maur d'Aubigny.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gaspard de George de Laugnac.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dey de Seraucourt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fourbin.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bouthillier of Chauvigny.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Brochond.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Abbot of Chalmazel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De Gyves.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:36398:18"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fabio Bruslard of Sillery.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>J. Bochard of Champigny.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Robert.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De Vaillac.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>P. Pecquot.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fr. de Gomer of Lusancy.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roubaud.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Francis de Vintimille.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Amelot.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Blache.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Le Camus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Du Fresnoy du Favouet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Odet Francis de Harcourt de Beuvron.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Clement of Poudeux.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>L. Rousseaux.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Langlois of Blacfort.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Villars, Agent generall of the Clergie of France.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Phelypeaux, Agent generall of the Clergie of France.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cheron, Promotor of the Assembly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Desmaretz, Antient Agent, &amp; Promotor of the Assembly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hardouin Rouxel de Medavi Grancey.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De Bezons, antient Agent, &amp; Secretary of the Assembly.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Hennequin, Secretarie of the Assembly.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="doctrine">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36398:18"/>
                  <head>THE DOCTRINE OF The most holy Catholique Church Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein'd in our profession of faith, and in the decrees of the holy Councill of Trent. <hi>OPPOSED To the Calumnies, lies, &amp; falseties, spred in the vvorks of the pretended Reformers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="part">
                     <head>Fidei Professio quae habetur in fine Concilii Tridentini.</head>
                     <p>EGO firma fide credo &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteor omnia &amp; singula, quae continentur in Symbolo Fidei, quo S. R. Ecclesia utitur, videlicet. <hi>CREDO</hi> in unum Deum Patrem Omnipotentem, factorem Caeli &amp; Terrae, visibilium omnium, &amp; invisibilium: &amp; in unum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>JESUM CHRISTUM</hi> Filium
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36398:19"/> Dei unigenitum; &amp; ex Patre natum ante omnia saecula, Deum de Deo, lumen de lumine, Deum verum de Deo vero, genitum non factum, consubstantialem Patri, per quem omnia facta sunt; qui propter nos Homines, &amp; propter nostram salutem descendit de Coelis: Et incarnatus est de Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu Sancto ex Maria Virgine; <hi>ET HOMO FACTUS EST;</hi> Crucifixus etiam pro nobis sub Pontio Pilato, passus &amp; sepultus est; &amp; resurrexit tertia die se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Scripturas; &amp; ascendit in caelum sedet ad dexteram Patris; &amp; iterum venturus est cum gloria judicare vivos &amp; mortuos; cujus regni non erit finis; Et in Spiritum Sanctum Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; vivificantem; qui ex Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre Filioque procedit; qui cum Patre &amp; Filio simul adoratur, &amp; conglorificatur; qui locutus est per Prophetas: Et unam sanctam Catholicam &amp; Apostolicam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiam. Confiteor unum Batisma in remissionem peccatorum; &amp; exspecto resurrectionem mortuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; vitam venturi saeculi. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:lang="eng" type="part">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:36398:18"/>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Firmly believe and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, all and every the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles Contein'd in the Simbole or Creed of faith, vsed in the holy Church of Rome to wit.</p>
                     <p>I believe in one God the father Almighty, maker of heaven &amp; earth,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36398:19"/> and of all things visible and invisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                     <p>And in one Lord JESUS-CHRIST, the only begotten son of God, and born of the father before all ages. God of God, light of light, true God of the true God: Begotten, not made, consubstantial to the father, by whom all things were made.</p>
                     <p>Who descended from heaven, for us men, and for our salvation: and takeing flesh of the virgin Mary, by the operation of the holy Ghost, BECAME MAN. He also was Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for us under Pontius Pilate, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and was buried, and rose again the third day, according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                     <p>Who ascended into heaven, and sits at the Right hand of the father, who will come again in glory, to Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the liveing and the dead, of whose kingdome there shall be no end.</p>
                     <p>And I believe in the holy Ghost, the Lord and giver of life, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the father and the son, who is adored and glorified Ioyntly with the father and the son, who spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke by the Prophets.</p>
                     <p>I believe one holy, Catholick, and Apostolick Church. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess one Baptisme for the Remission of sins. I expect the Resur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, and life in the world to come. <hi>Amen.</hi> that is so be it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36398:19"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>ARTICLE THE FIRST.</hi> Of Scriptures Canonicall, and of Tradition.</head>
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="continuation">
                        <head>PROFESSIO Fidei.</head>
                        <p>Apostolicas, &amp; Ecclesiasticas Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiones, reliquas{que} ejusdem Ecclesiae Observationes &amp; Constitutiones fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missimè admitto &amp; amplector. Item Sacram Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram juxta eum sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum, quem tenuit &amp; tenet Sancta Mater Ecclesia, cujus est judicare de vero sensu &amp; Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione Scriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, admitto.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="20" facs="tcp:36398:20"/>
                           <hi>1. Concilium Trident. ses. 4. in Decreto de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicis Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris:</hi> Sancta Synodus Ortodoxorum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum exempla se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuta, omnes libros tam veteris, quam novi Testamenti, suscipit ac venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Sacrorum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò Librorum indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem huic decreto adscribendum cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2. Fidei Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessio:</hi> nec eam <hi>Scripturam,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam nisi juxta.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36398:20"/> unanimem consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum Patrum acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam &amp; interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabor.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Conc. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. In eodem Decreto de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. Scripturis:</hi> Necnon Traditiones ipsas, tùm ad Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, tùm ad mores pertinentes, tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam vel ore tenùs à Christo, vel à Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu sancto dictatas &amp; continuâ succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sione in Ecclesia Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica conservatas, pari pietatis affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu ac reverentiâ suscipit ac venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="continuation">
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36398:19"/>
                        <head>THE CONTINUATION of the doctrine of the holy Catholick Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein'd in our profession of faith, and in the decrees of the holy Councill of Trent.</head>
                        <p>I Receave, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace most firmly the Apostolick &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastick traditions, &amp; the other Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, and obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of the Same Church. I receave the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36398:20"/> holy Scriptures accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the sense, which our holy mother the Church holds and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, unto whom it appertains to iudge of the true sense &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the holy Scriptures. The holy council of Trent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of the orthodox fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers receaves all those books, as well of the old, as of the new testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of which à Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue is placed at the End of their decrees.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. I will never use nor interpret, those books,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36398:20"/> But according to the unanimous consent, and oppinion of the holy fathers of the Church.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. The holy councill receaves with the same Respect and equall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ion the traditions whether they concerne the faith or man̄ers, as spoaken by the mouth of JESUS CHRIST or by the holy Ghost, and which have been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church by a Continuall succession.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="calumnies">
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36398:19"/>
                        <head>THE CALUMNIES Lies and falsities, spred &amp; publish'd in the worcks of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Reformers, against the Doctrine of the Catholick Church.</head>
                        <p>THat with the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Guilielmus VVitaxerus Theologiae Doctor &amp; Professor Cantabrigiensis in disputatione de sacra Scriptura contra Bellarminum &amp;c, Controversiâ 16. q. 6. pag. 665, Editionis Herbodae Nassoviorum anni 1600. <hi>Patet illos Haereticos</hi> (de quibus S. Irenaeus) <hi>per omnia similes fuisse nostris Papistis; Scripturas enim repudiabant.</hi>
                           </note> of whom S. Jreneus speaks, wee Reject the holy Scriptures;<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Georgius Dounamus Episcopus D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>erensis in Libro cui titulus:</hi> Papa Antichr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stus <hi>L 3. c. 6. pag. 175. Edit Londinensis annis 1620.</hi> Sacras Scripturas cum Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistis imperfectionis arguunt &amp; insufficientiae, quam certam esse notam Haereticorum Irenaeus observavit. <hi>Titulus hujus captis est:</hi> Catologus veterum haeresium, quas Ecclesia Romana renovavit.</note> that with the Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists wee accuse them of imperfection; that<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputationum Theologicarum in Academia Sedanensi variis tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus habitarum à Pastoribus &amp; Theologiae Professoribus; Petro Molinaeo. Iacobo Capello, Abrahamo Ramburtio, Samuele Maresio, Alexandro Colvino, Ludovico le Blanc, Iosua le Vasseur, Iacobo Alpaeo de S. Maurice, thesi 26. de meritis operum par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. 2. Edit. Genevensis anni 1661, tom. 1. pag. 69. <hi>Scripturam quidem contemnere Pontificiis solemne est.</hi>
                           </note> wee under value them; that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36398:20"/>
                           <note n="(d)" place="bottom">Andreas Rivetus Pictavus Theologiae Doctor &amp; Professor in Academia Batava in Catholico Orthodoxo, seu summâ Controversiarum adversus Guilielmum Bailium Iesuitam, quaest. 1. Prooemiali de Haeresibus pag 27. Edit. 3. Ludg. Batavo. anno 1630. <hi>Papistae communiter docent Scripturas non esse necessarias, &amp; Ecclesiam iis posse carere.</hi> Eadem repetit tract. 1. q, 6. §. 1. tom. eodem 1, pag. 95. &amp; in Thesauro disputat. Sedanensium jam laudato thes. 14. tom. 1. pag. 61. <hi>Cum negent</hi> (Pontificii) <hi>Scripturam esse necessariam.</hi>
                           </note> wee comonly teach; that the Scriptures are not necessarie, and the Church can pass without them; that<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>In eodem Thesauro disputat. Sedanens. thes. 12, tom. 1. pag. 6.</hi> In Ecclesia Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana traditiones non scriptae, multò pluris fiunt Scripturâ, earumque est longè major auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, quàm Scripturae, usque adeò, ut adversarii quidquid Scriptura habet autoritatis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lint pendere ex autoritate Traditionis Ecclesiae. <hi>Andreas Rivetus ubi suprâ; Georgius Dounamus ubi suprâ.</hi>
                           </note> wee prefer tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to the holy Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res; that wee give them more authority, and that the Scriptures have no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority but by tradition; that<note n="(f)" place="bottom">In eodem Thesauro disputat. Sedan thes. 14. cit. de perfectione Scripturae tom, 1. pag. 61. <hi>Traditio Ecclesiae</hi> (juxtà Pontificios) <hi>emendat Scripturam &amp; mandata Dei immutat &amp; dispensat ab Apostolo.</hi>
                           </note> according, to us, tradition corrects the Scriptures; that tradition changeth the comande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and that she dispenseth, against the Apostle; that<note n="(g)" place="bottom">In eodem Thesauro th. 7. de summo Controvers. Judice tom. 1. pag. 26. <hi>Onerant</hi> (Pontificii) <hi>Scripturam plaustro convitiorum, vocando eam regulam mutam, lapidem scandali, nasum cereum, gladium ancipitem,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; in thesi de perfect. sacrae Scrip. 14. eod. to. 1. pag. 61, eadem repetit verba.</note> wee call the Scriptures.</p>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:36398:20"/>
                        <p>a dumb rule, a Rock of scandale, a nose of wax, a knife that cuts both ways;</p>
                        <p>That<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>In eodem Thesauro disput. Sedan th. 13. de sum. Controver. Iudice tom. 1. pag. 28.</hi> Ecclesia Romana est suprà Scripturam, Papa verò suprà Ecclesiam Romanam, hinc efficitur Papam duobus gradibus supra Scripturam eminere.</note> wee raise the Roman Church above the Scriptures by one degree, &amp; the Pope by two degrees; that<note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ibidem th. 2. pag. 25. to. 1.</hi> Invenit Sathan hanc viam introducendi per cunicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los Atheïsmum in Ecclesiam, &amp; labefactandi autoritatem Verbi divini, dum ab humana autoritate suspenditur, &amp; statuitur verbo Dei credendum esse, quia id homines volunt, &amp; id Papa sanxit. <hi>Et th. 1. ibid.</hi> Quaeritur an major fit Dei, quàm hominum autoritas. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique th. 32. pag 31. ibid.</hi> Hoc pestilentissimo dogmate, quo Ecclesia statuitur Iudex &amp; Scripturae haec dignitas adimitur, certum est viâ compendiosissima iri ad atheismum &amp; totam Religionem de putri filo suspendi.</note> our Doctrine concerning this point, leads to Atheisme, &amp; to the over throwing of all Religion; &amp; that<note n="(k)" place="bottom">In eodem Thesauro disputat. th. 31. pag. 65, tom. 1. <hi>Habent tamen Pontificii Autores quibus Traditionem non scriptam tueantur,</hi> (eosdem Autores mox appellat.) <hi>Phariseos, Montanistas, Carpocratianos.</hi> Andreas Rivetus Catholic. Orthodoxi seu summ. Controvers. q. 1. Prooemiali de Haeresibus pag. 27. &amp; 28. <hi>Simoniani referente Irenaeo gloriabantur de iis quae non sunt scripta; sed solùm vivâ voce tradita,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Hoc idem Papistae faciunt.</hi> Ioannes Heydeggerus in Anatome Historico Theologica Concilii Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentini quaest. de trad ad sess. 4. Conc. Trid. tom. 1. pag. 87. Edit Gesnerian. 1672. <hi>Perventum in Concilio hoc nostro</hi> (Tridentino) <hi>ad canonisationem traditionum eo in sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su; quem nunquam vera Ecclesia tenuit; imò quem in Haereticis damnavit.</hi>
                           </note> wee have for authors but the Pharises, the Disciples of Simon the Magician, &amp; the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanists.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>ARTICLE II.</hi> Of the Efficacy, number and ceremonies of the Sacraments, of pennance and auricular Confession.</head>
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="continuation">
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Professio Fidei:</hi> Profiteor quoque septem esse verè &amp; proprè Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta novae Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, à Iesu Christo Domino nostro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituta, atque ad salutem humani generis, licet, non omnia singulis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaria: scilicet Baptismum, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmationem, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charistiam.</p>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>
                        <p>Poenitentiam, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremam-Vnctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Ordinem &amp; Matrimonium.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Conc. Trid. sess. 7. can. 8.</hi> Si quis dixerit per ipsa novae Legis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta ex ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re operato non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri gratiam; sed solam fidem divinae promissionis ad gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam consequendam sufficere, Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma sit.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36398:22"/>
                           <hi>1. Idem Conc. sess. 6. cap. 6.</hi> Disponuntur autem ad ipsam justitiam, dum excitati divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ gratiâ &amp; adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti fidem ex auditu concipientes, liberè moventur in Deum, credentes vera esse, quae divinitùs reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata &amp; promissa sunt; atque illud imprimis, à Deo justificari impium per gratiam ejus, per redemptionem, quae est in Christo Iesu; &amp; dum peccatores se esse intelligentes, à divinae Iustitiae ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, quo uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36398:22"/> concutiuntur, ad considerandam Dei misericordiam se convertendo, in spem eriguntur, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes Deum sibi propter Christum proprium fore, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumque tanquam omnis justitiae fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem diligere in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt, ac proptereà moventur adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus peccata per odium aliquod &amp; detestationem, hoc est, per eam poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam, quam an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Baptismum agi
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36398:23"/> oportet. Denique dum proponunt sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere Baptismum, inchoare novam vitam &amp; servare divina mandata.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="27" facs="tcp:36398:23"/>
                           <hi>1. Professio Fidei:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="28" facs="tcp:36398:24"/>
                        <p>Et ex his <hi>(Sacramentis)</hi> Baptismum, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmationem &amp; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem sine sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio reiterari non posse.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1 Conc. Trid. sess. 14. can 6.</hi> Si quis negaverit Confessionem Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentalem, vel institutam, vel ad salutem necessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am esse jure divino, aut dixerit modum secretè confitendi soli Sacerdoti, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> alienum esse ab institutione &amp; mandato Christi, vel inventum esse humanum, Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma sit.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2. Idem Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Trid. Can. 7. ejusdem Sess. 14.</hi> Si quis dixerit in Sacramento Poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae, ad remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionem peccatorum, necessarium non es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se jure divino, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteri omnia &amp; sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula peccata mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia, &amp; quorum memoria, cum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita &amp; diligenti praemedicatione ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beatur,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36398:24"/> etiam oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culta, &amp; quae sunt contra duo ultima Decalogi Praecepta, &amp; circonstantias, quae speciem peccati mutant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema sit.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Professio Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei:</hi> Receptos quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que &amp; approbatos Ecclesiae Catholicae ritus, in supradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omnium Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentorum solen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, administratione, recipio &amp; admitto.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="continuation">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>
                        <head>DOCTRINE OF THE CHURCH.</head>
                        <p>I 1. Confess also that there is truly and properly seaven Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the new law, instituted by our lord JESUS-CHRIST, and necessarie to the salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, although all of them are not to every one.</p>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>
                        <p>These Sacraments are Baptisme, Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Euchariste, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Extreame-Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, holy Orders, &amp; Matrimonie.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. If any one shall say, that thêse Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the new law do not Conferr grace of them selves; but that faith a lone in the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne promisses is suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to obteine grace, let him be Anathema.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36398:22"/>1. The receavers are disposed to Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, when excited &amp; assisted by the grace of God, receaveing faith by hearing, carrying them selves freely to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, &amp; holding for veritable, those things that have been promised &amp; Revealed by God, &amp; this point above all others that the sinner is justified of God by his grace, &amp; by the Redemption acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red through JESUS-CHRIST. Then know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing them selves to be sinners.</p>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:36398:22"/>
                        <p>with fear of the divine Justice, by which they are profitably stirr'd up to the Consideration of Gods mercie, &amp; are raised into hopes, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting that God will be mercifull unto them, for the love of JESUS CHRIST; and begin to love him as the fountain of all Justice
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36398:23"/> &amp; therfore they are moved against sin, by a certaine hatred &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testation; that is to say by Repentance, that ought to precede Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme. To the end that when they Resolue to be baptised, to begin
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36398:23"/> a new life, and keep the Comandements of God.</p>
                        <p>I believe that three
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36398:24"/> of the Sacraments; to witt, Baptisme, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, &amp; holy order, cannot be administred twice to any one body without sacriledge.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. If any one shall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that Sacramentall confession, either to have been instituted, or that 'tis necessary to sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by divine Right, or says that the manner of Confessing secretly to the Preist alone, as 'tis used in the holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, is not conformable to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, and precept of JESUS-CHRIST; but that 'tis a humane invention, let him be Anathema.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. If any one shall say, that in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Repentance, it is not necessary by divine Right, for the Remission of sins, to confesse all and every mortall sin of which they can Remember, after haveing before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand carefully exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd themselves, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the most secret
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36398:24"/> sins, which are against the two last Comande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the table, &amp; the circumstances, which change the kind of sin &amp;c. let him be Anathema.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. I receave and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt the Ceremonies aproved by the holy Catholick Church, in the solemn administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="calumnies">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>
                        <head>THE CALUMNIES OF THE PRETENDED REFORMED.</head>
                        <p>THat<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>The Confession of faith of the pretended Reformed of France art. 28.</hi> Wee condemn the assemblies of the Papists, seeing the pure truth of God is banished, that the Sacrements are Corrupted, adulterated, &amp; falsefied in the whole.</note> in the Church the Sacraments are corrupted, Adulterated &amp; falsefied; that<note n="(b)" place="bottom">Theodorus Beza Vezelius in Antithesi Papa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>us &amp; Christianismi tractationum Theologicarum Edit. 2. Genev. an. 1576. tom. 1 pag. 71. <hi>Satis apparet Sacramenta indignissimis modis pollui ac perdi, in Papistica Synagoga, quae Catholicae Ecclesiae nomen sibi falsò vendicat.</hi>
                           </note> they are treated after an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy manner; that<note n="(c)" place="bottom">Joannes Calvinus in respons. ad Cardinalem Sadoletum opusculorum ultimae Edit. Amstelodamensis anni 1667. pag. 111. <hi>Sacramenta ostendimus, multis profanis opinionibus inquinata.</hi>
                           </note> they are polluted with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers prophane opinions; that<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Martinus Lutherus in Libro de Captivitate Babylonica tom. 2. Edit. VVitem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergensis anni 1558. fol 75.</hi> Impulsi sunt tantum tribuere Sacramentis novae Legis, ut prodesse ea statuerent, etiam iis, qui in peccatis mortalibus sunt, nec requiri fidem aut gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam; sed sufficere non posuisse obicem, hoc est, actuale propositum denuò peccandi. <hi>Philippus Melancton in Apologia Confessionis Augustanae titulo de numero &amp; usu Sacramento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tom. 1. Edit VVitembergensis.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>anni 1562. fol. 95.</hi> Damnamus totum populum Scholasticorum, qui docent, quod Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta non ponenti obicem conferunt gratiam ex opere operato, sine bono motu utentis. Haec simpliciter Iudaica opinio est, sentire quia per ceremonias justificamur sine bono motu cordis, hoc est, sine fide, &amp; tamen haec impia &amp; periculosa opinio magna autoritate docetur in toto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gno Pontificio. <hi>Confessio ista Augustana art. 13. apud eumdem Melanctonem eodem tom. 1. fol. 41. &amp; in Syntagmate Confessionum Fidei:</hi> Damnant Pharisaïcam opinionem, quae fingit homines justos esse, propter usum Sacrementorum ex opere operato sine bono motu utentium. <hi>Martinus Kemnitius in 2. parte Examinis Concil. Trident. ad can. 8. sess. 7. pag. 22. Edit. Genevens. anni 1614, Franciscus Burmanus Theologus Doctor &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor in Academia Batava, in Synopsi Theologica l. 7. c. 4. §. 36, Edit. Trajecten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis ad Rhenum anni 1672. pag. 323. &amp; 324.</hi> Per opus operatum in Concilio Tridentino ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam Sacramentorum celebrationem intelligebant, quae non ponentibus obicem peccati mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis; etsi alioqui fide &amp; pietate vacuis, salutaris gratiae causa, &amp; instrumentum sit.</note>
                           <pb n="22" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>wee teach that the,</p>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36398:21"/>
                        <p>Sacraments Conferr gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to the receavers not with standing they have not the least good disposition in their hearts, and their being in the state of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall sin provided onely that they have not actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly formed à designe to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt a new sin; that wee teach this impious, &amp; pharisaicall oppinion with full authority in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church; That<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 6. de Baptismo parte 3. tom. 1. pag. 779.</hi> Id volunt fieri, ex opere operato, id est, vi nudae actionis, nullam enim attentionem aut devotionem requiri in eo qui baptisatur, etiamsi sit adultus. Nam si adultus dormiens aut incogitans &amp; aliud agens baptisetur, statuunt eum Baptismo regenerari, eique fidem infundi, satis esse ad efficaciam Baptismi, si baptisa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus non ponat obicem, id est, Baptismum data operâ non aversetur: <hi>Et anteà pag. 753. the. 9. de Sacramentis in genere part. 2.</hi> Actionem dicunt valere ex opere operato, quando nuda actio &amp; celebratio est efficax, etiamsi nulla dispositio, aut de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votio accedat in administrante, aut recipiente &amp; nulla sit recipientis attentio, modo ne datâ operâ ponat obicem &amp; contra nitatur.</note> wee dispense even those that receaves them from.</p>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:36398:22"/>
                        <p>Being attentife to what they do, &amp; that according to us, it sufficeth, that they do not oppose them selves with a formed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign to that which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred to them; that<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ibidem th. 20. pag. 7 55.</hi> In Sacramentis suscipiendis, evagationi mentis &amp; supini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taeti parta est securitas, quasi ex ipsa indevotione, Sacramentis pretium accesserit.</note> wee give occasion to believe, that the indevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they have for them, doth augment their value; that<note n="(g)" place="bottom">Ibidem de Sacramentis in genere part. 1. th. 27. pag. 750. <hi>Cum Deo sic agunt quasi vinciretur syllabis &amp; formulis astringeretur, quae labes à magica Disciplinâ in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem transi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>t.</hi> Guillielmus Bucanus Theologiae Professor in Academia Lausanensi, loco 46. de Sacramentis, paragr. 75. pag. 650. Edit. 3. Bernae Helvetiorum anni 1605. <hi>vi verborum, quasi migicâ incantatione &amp;c.</hi>
                           </note> wee make the Efficacie of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Consist in a Certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Enchantment or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick. That<note n="(h)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 23. de Sacremento Poenitent. parte 2. tom. 1. pag. 684. <hi>Figmentum est audax velle ut Spiritus Sanctus in attritis sit agens intrinse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, nec moveat eos motu intrinseco.</hi> Joannes Heydeggerus Anatom Conc. Trident. tom. 1. pag. 558.</note> wee would have the holy ghost work in their hearts, when he disposes them to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, whether he moves them interiourly or not.</p>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:36398:22"/>
                        <p>that<note n="(i)" place="bottom">Idem Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 26. de Sacramento Poenit. part. 2. to. 1. pag. 685. <hi>Constans est Pontificiorum sententia non esse necesse conteri, de peccatis veniali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, sed tantùm de mortalibus.</hi>
                           </note> it is a Constant opinion amongst us, that it is not necessarie to have sorrow for our veniall sins; that<note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Joannes Calvinus in opusculo de vera Ecclesiae reformandae ratione opuscul. pag. 276;</hi> Expertae sunt piae animae, quàm dira esset carnificina, cùm ad hujuscemod. Confessionem adigebantur. <hi>Franciscus Burmannus in Synopsi Theolog. L. 6. c. 9. §. 41. tom 2. pag. 259:</hi> In Confessione auriculari culpamus tyrannidem conscientiis impositam. <hi>Thesaurus dis. Sedan, th. 31. de Sacram. Poenit. parte 3. to. 1 pag. 691:</hi> Est Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessio carnificina animarum, &amp; laqueus injectus conscientiis, ac dura tyrannis. <hi>Joannes Heydeggerus in Anatome Conc. Trid. tom. 1. pag. 564.</hi> Secreta Confessio est carnifii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina animi, desperationis laqueus. <hi>Et mox:</hi> hamus est Sacerdotum &amp; Ecclesiae, cujus hoc modo mirificè crescunt divitiae, autoritas ac formidabilis potentia.</note> Confession is the Butchery of souls, &amp; the tyrannie of Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; à trap to dispair &amp; the fish hook of the Preists &amp; Chruch, for to Enrich, &amp; give themselves, a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable authority; that<note n="(l)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. thesi 6. de Sacramento Poenitent, parte 4. tom. 1. pag.. 699: <hi>Doctrina de Potestate judiciariâ Sacerdotum, bellum Deo indicit, &amp; est prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipua pars misterii iniquitatis.</hi> Franciscus Burmannus in Synopsi Theolog. l. 6. c. 9. §. 41. tom. 2. pag. 259: <hi>Sacrilegam hominum potestatem in hoc negotio damnamus.</hi> Petrus Martyr Vermilius Florentinus sacrarum Litterarum olim in Schola Tygurina Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesso, Locorum communium classe 3. cap. 4. §. 32. Edit. Tygurinae anni 1587. pag. 528. <hi>Auricularis Papistarum Confessio superstitiosa est.</hi>
                           </note> the power to forgive sins
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36398:23"/> is a declaration of warr against God; that 'tis a sacriledge, &amp; the Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion that precedes it is full of superstition; that<note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Theodorus Beza in Antithesi Papatus &amp; Christianismi tom. 1. oper. seu tract. Theologic. pag. 65.</hi> Poenitentiae Sacramentum excogitarunt, &amp;c. Nos autem in hac vere diabolica doctrina, &amp;c. Itaque Papistarum d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ctrinam ut blaspheman, &amp;c.</note> the Doctrine of the Church touching Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, is Diabolicall &amp; Blasphemie; that<note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>In the advertissement or Catechisme of Charenton pag. 38. of the book in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled:</hi> The forme of prayer, &amp;c. <hi>of the Edition of 1670.</hi> Says tis in the Confirmation where there is nothing but mier apishness without the least ground. <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico Orthodoxo seu Summa Controves. tract. 2 quaest. 25. §. 3. tom. 1. pag. 498.</hi> Osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant nobis, unquâm hanc artem à veteribus fuisse traditam, &amp; magiae eas <hi>(Ceremonias)</hi> insimulare desinemus; ni faciant semper pro diaboli artibus, iis, quas servum suum Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linem Tyaneum docuerat, similibus, hebebimus, de quo Philostratus, testatur, quod certis gesticulationibus diabolos ejecerit. <hi>Ibidem quaest. 27.</hi> §. <hi>3. pag. 750.</hi> Potissimae eorum <hi>(Romanorum)</hi> Ceremoniae sunt supestitiosae, frigidae, aut ridiculae, verboque Dei contrariae. <hi>Joannes Calvinus l. 4. Institut. cap. 19. paragr. 7. pag 389. de Confirmatione loquens:</hi> Vacuum &amp; frigidum signum, quod simiae isti faciunt mimiticè tantùm &amp; sine re effingunt <hi>Mox:</hi> Hoc non à me, sed à Domino audacter pronuntio: qui oleum vocant oleum salutis, salutem, quae in Christo est abjurant, Christumque abnegant, &amp;c. <hi>ibid. §. 10.</hi> Oleum diaboli mendacio pollutum. Tu ne pinguedinem foetore dumtaxat halitus tui inquinatam &amp; verborum murmure incantatam, &amp;c. audes Christi Sacramento <hi>(Baptismo)</hi> opponere. <hi>Theodorus Beza in Antithesi Papatus &amp; Christianismi tractat Theolog. tom. 1. pag. 69.</hi> Infinitis adhibisis plusquàm magicis Ceremoniis, oleum ipsum millies adoratus, &amp;c. neque apud eos ullum sacrum Mysterium, absque magico isto oleo consecratur. <hi>Ioannes Heydeggerus in Anatome Concil. Trident. ad sess. 22. Canon. de Ceremoniis Missae, tom. 2. pag. 802.</hi> Pleraeque Ceremoniae debentur pravae imitationi, vel Gentilis; vel Iudaismi <hi>(mox)</hi> Histrionicus ritus, quo toties Sacerdes se Populi precibus commandat. <hi>Et tom. 1. pag. 320. de ritibus Baptismi loquens:</hi> assuerunt ritus quos faciunt partem Sacramenti, &amp; quibus mysterium affingunt, partim sordidos &amp; impios, partem mimicos, &amp;c. Sordidas illas actiones, veluti cum ad pellendum daemonium sacrificus ter exsufflat in faciem infantis, &amp; accipiens de saliva ores sui tangit ejus nares &amp; aures, quam Ceremoniam à Messallianis &amp; Euchetis mutuati sunt, perindè ac si diaboli sint Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piones salivâ extinguendi. <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico Orthodoxo seu Summa Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troves, tract. 2, quaest. 17. paragr. 3. tom. 1. pag. 417. de aqua lustrali seu benedicta
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36398:23"/>loquens:</hi> Gestibus ridiculis incantara, &amp;c. Ipsissimae diabolis sunt insidiae: Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius Hemero-Baptis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>as, quotidie se baptisantes, non purgandi corporis causâ; sed peccatorum remissionis gratiâ refellebat: ea haeresis hodierno die in Papatu viget, &amp;c. <hi>Ibidem paragr. 5.</hi> Papistae aquam lustralem à Gentilium Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis sunt mutuati, in quibus haec erat una ex vulgatissimis. <hi>Ioannes Calvinus l. 4. Institut. c. 17. §. 15. pag. 369.</hi> Consecratio tantumdem apud eos valet ac magica incantatio. <hi>Synoposis putioris Theologiae conscripta per Ioannem Polyandrum, Andaeam Rivetum, Antonium walaeum, &amp; Antonium Thysium Theologiae Doctores &amp; Professores in Academia Lugdunensi apud Batavos, disputat. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>. thesi 37. pag. 6. 9. Edit. Elsevir. an. 1625.</hi> Iure a Pontificiorum sacrilegâ audaciâ abhorremus, qui Ceremonias Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Institutioni Christi addiderunt, quas meritorias esse &amp; vim quandam arcanam &amp; spiritualem in sanctificando habere, partemque divini cultus efficere decernunt. <hi>Burnet in his remarks upon the acts of the last Generall assembly of the Clergie of France, printd at London 1683. pag 54.</hi> to which <hi>(Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies)</hi> they atribute the virtue to cast out Divills, to preserue body &amp; soul, to heale all distempers temporal and spirituall: this maner of charmes is one of the Cheifest points of the pagan Religion. is it not to behold Godwith the Same Eye, that Pagans do, is it not to Imitate them in their Customes, to attain to virtue by charmes.</p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Theodorus Beza in brevi Confessione Fidei art. 24. tractat. Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. tom. 1. pag. 83.</hi> Ecclesiam infinitis Ceremoniis onerarunt, &amp; ita quidem ut Christianismum, non tantùm in Iudaismum; sed etiam in Paganismum omnin ò transfomarint. <hi>Ioannes Calvinus in l. de verâ Ecclesiae Reforman lae ratione, opusculorum pag. 297. Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico Orthodoxo seu Summa Controves. quaest. 1. proemiali de Haeresibus tom. 1. pag. 41.</hi> Ethnophrones apud Damascenum, &amp; Nicetam habentur Haeretici; quia cum Gentium instituta sequerentur, in alliis erant Christiani: Papistae fere in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus suis Ceremoniis sunt Ethnophrones, &amp;c. <hi>Georgius Dounamus libro cui titulus:</hi> Papa Antichristus, <hi>l. 3. c. 6. § 2. pag. 176.</hi> Cum Cerinthianis &amp; Ebionitis addicti sunt ex parte Iudaismo, multòsque Iudaeorum ritus, Christi morte antiquatos observant.</p>
                           </note>
                           <pb n="26" facs="tcp:36398:23"/>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation is but a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36398:23"/> Ape-ish trick; that the holy oyle is blessed by cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies wors then magick.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36398:24"/> that 'tis an oyle of the Divill.</p>
                        <p>That wee can not say 'tis necessary to salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without Renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing JESUS-CHRIST; that the ceremonies used in the Church are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments of Magick, like unto those which the Divill taught to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo of Thyané his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; that they are su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestitious, prophane, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, Rediculous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from Pagans, Iews, and Ethnophornean he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, &amp;c. That ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lywater is a Renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heresie of the Hemero-Baptists, that the Ceremonies of the mass is but a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; that wee affix to those ceremonies a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to give grace, &amp; for to cast out Divills by a kind of Charme in Imitation of Pagans; that by these ceremonies the Church has chang'd Christianisme, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into Judaisme, but also into Paganisme; that of the Sacraments
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:36398:24"/> wee make Jdols, that<note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Franciscus Burmannus in Synopsi Teologicâ l. 7. c. 5. §. 11 pag. 330.</hi> Opinio operis operati uti voce, ita magis sensu barbara, cum externis signis sacrilegam potestatem attribuat, proq́ue ipso Christo externorum rituum Idola Ecclesiae tractanda &amp; colendae offerat.</note> wee teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to adore them.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36398:25"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>ARTICLE III.</hi> Of Justification &amp; Merrits.</head>
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="continuation">
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Professio Fidei:</hi> Omnia &amp; singula, quae de peccato originali &amp; de Iustificatione, in Sacro-sanctâ Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentina Synodo, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finita &amp; declarata fuerunt amplector &amp; recipio.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2. Conc. Trid. sess. 5. in Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to de peccato originali, §. 3.</hi> Si quis Adae pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quod origine unum est, &amp; propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatione, non imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione transfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36398:25"/> omnibus, inest unicuique propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, vel per huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae naturae vires vel per aliud remediū asserit tolli, quàm per meritum unius Mediatoris Iesu Christi Domini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stri, qui nos Deo reconciliavit, in Sanguine suo, aut negat ipsum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti Iesu meritum, per Baptismi Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Ecclesiae ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tè collatum, tàm adultis, quàm parvulis appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36398:26"/> Anathema fit.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> §. <hi>5.</hi> Si quis per <hi>1. C.</hi> Domini nostri gratiam, quae in Baptismate confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, reatum Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis Peccati re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti negat, aut etiam asserit, non tolli totum id quod veram &amp; propriam peccati rationem habet; sed illud tantum dicit radi, aut non imputari, Anathema sit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Manere autem in baptisatis concupis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hanc quam aliquando A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolus peccatum appellat, declarat
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36398:26"/> sancta Synodus Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiam Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, nunquàm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellexisse peccatum appellari, quod ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè &amp; propriè in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis peccatum sit; sed quia ex peccato est, &amp; ad pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum inclinat.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="34" facs="tcp:36398:27"/>
                           <hi>1. Idem Concil. sess. 6. can. 1.</hi> Si quis dixerit homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem suis operibus, quae vel per huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae naturae vires, vel per legis Doctrinam fiunt, absque divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na per Iesum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stum gratia posse ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stificari coram Deo, Anathema sit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2. Can. 3.</hi> Si quis dixerit sine praeveni ente Spiritus sancti
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36398:27"/> inspiratione, atque ejus adjutorie, hominem credere, sperare, diligere, aut poenitere posse, sicut oportet, ut ei justificationis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia conferatur, Anathema sit.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Conc. Trid. fess. 6. cap. 8.</hi> Gratis justificari ideò dicimur; quia nihil eorum quae justificationem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedunt, sivè fides, sive opera, ipsam justificationis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam promerentur.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36398:28"/>
                           <hi>1. In eadem sess. can. 4.</hi> Si quis dixerit libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum hominis arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trium à Deo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; excitatum nihil cooperari assentiendo Deo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citanti atque vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canti, quo ad obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendam juctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis gratiam se disponat ac praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, neque posse dissentire si velit; sed velut inanime quoddam nihil om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninò agere, merè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que passivè se habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, Anathema sit.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Ibid. can. 9.</hi> Si quis dixerit sola Fide Impium justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, ita ut intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligat nihil aliud re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiri, quod ad ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stificationis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam consequendam cooperetur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema sit.</p>
                        <p>* <hi>Et can. 11.</hi> Si quis dixerit homines justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari, vel sola imputatione ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitiae
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36398:28"/> Christi, vel sola peccatorum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missione, exclusa gratiâ &amp; charitate, quae in cordibus eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, per Spiritum sanctum diffundun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c. Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma sit.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Ibid. can. 25.</hi> Si quis dixerit in quolibet opere bono Iustum saltem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nialiter peccare, aut quod intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius est, morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema sit.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2. Et Can. 26.</hi> Si quis dixerit Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stos non debere pro bonis operibus, quae in Deo fuerint fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta, exspectare, &amp; sperare aeternam retributionem à Deo per ejus mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiam, &amp; Iesu Christi meritum, si benè agendo, &amp; divina mandata custodiendo usque in finem perseve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raverint, Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma sit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="continuation">
                        <head>DOCTRINE OF THE CHURCH.</head>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36398:25"/>
                        <p>I 1. Receave all those points which were decided in the holy councill of Trent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning originall sin, &amp; Justification.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. If any one shall maintaine, that the sin of Adam, which is one in its source, &amp; which is transmitted unto all by generation, &amp; not by imitation becomes proper to every one,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36398:25"/> may be blotted out, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by force of huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nature, or by any other means, but by the merits of JESUS-CHRIST our lord and onely mediator, who reconciled us by his blood; or whoever denies, that the same meritts of JESUS-CHRIST, are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, as well to those that are of age, as to Infants, by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptisme
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36398:26"/> Conferr'd according to the forme and Custome of the Church, let him be Anathema.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. If any one denies that by the grace of our Lord JESUS-CHRIST, which is Conferr'd in Baptisme, the guilt of originall sinn: is Remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or hodls that all that is properly &amp; truly of sin is not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; but is only as it were shaved, or is not Imputed, let him be Anathema the holy Councill neverthelesse Confesseth &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth that.</p>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:36398:26"/>
                        <p>à Concupiscence, or the Inclination to sin, remains notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the persons Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated by Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; but also declares, that this Concupiscen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle sometimes calls sin was never taken, nor understood by the Catholick Church, as à reall sin.</p>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:36398:27"/>
                        <p>that Remains to (spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke properly) in the persons baptised; but that it has been call'd by the name of sin, because it is an Effect of sin, &amp; that it indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to sin.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. If any one shall say that à man may be Iustified before God by his proper works, done onely by his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall force, or by the lights of faith, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout the grace of God merited by JESUS-CHRIST, let him be Anathema.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. If any one shall say that without the Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the holy ghost
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36398:27"/> and without his helpe, a man may make acts of faith, of hope &amp; Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity &amp; Repent, such as he ought to do for to obteine the grace of Justification, let him be Anathema.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Wee are said to be Justified gratis; be cause in Effect nothing of all that precedes Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, let it be faith, let it be works, do not merrit, even the grace of Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="36" facs="tcp:36398:28"/>1. If any one shall say, that free will moved &amp; excited by God, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing his consent to God, who excited him, &amp; who calls him, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operat's in nothing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards prepareing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sefe, &amp; putting him in à state to obteine the grace of Justification; &amp; that he canot refuse his consent, if he will; but that he is like à thing without soul unable to act any thing, &amp; only passive, let him be ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. If any one shall say that man is Justified by faith alone after the maner as is understood therby, that for to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the grace of Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, there needs no other thing, to Coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, let him be Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. If any one shall say that men are Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied either by the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imputation of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:36398:28"/> Justice of JESUS-CHRIST, or by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of sins only, Excludeing the grace of Charity, which is Effused in to their he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arts, by the holy Ghost, let him be Anathema.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. If any one shall say that in any good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke whatever, the Just sinneth at least venial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or even, that which is yet more insuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that he sins Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, let him be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. If any one shall say that the Just, for their good works done in the grace of God, ought not to expect, nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe from him the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Recompense, by his mercie, &amp; by the meritts of JESUS-CHRIST, provided he perseveres in doing well to the End, &amp; in keeping his Comande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, let him be Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="calumnies">
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:36398:25"/>
                        <head>CALUMNIES OF THE PRETENDED REFORMED.</head>
                        <p>THat<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>In Confessione Fidei Ecclesiarum Belgicarum oblata Synodo Dordrechtanae, inter acta hujus Synodi pag. 308 primae partis Edit. Elsevir. anni 2600. approbata est haec Confessio in Synodo protestantium Galliae Vitriaci habita 25. Maii anno 1583.</hi> Necessarium est, aut omnia, quae ad salutem nostram requiruntur in Iesu Christo non esse, aut si in eo sunt omnia, tum eum qui fide Iesum Christum possidet, totum salutem habere: asserere itaque Iesum Christum minimè sufficere; sed aliis quoque praeter ipsum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>pus esse, horrenda omninò in Deum blasphemia est. Nam inde sequeretur, ipsum Christum ex parte tantùm servatorem esse. Meritò igitur dicimus cum Paulo nos sola Fide justificari.</note> 'tis Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie against God, to say, that wee are not Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified by faith alone; &amp; that 'tis not enough, to be, &amp; have faith in JESUS-CHRIST; that to expound<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disput. Sedan. th. 22. de Justificatione patte 1. tom. 1. pag. 625.</hi> Hominibus quibus propositum est Christianam Fidem cuniculis subruere &amp; machinis ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere, Sathan suggessit compendiosam viam, quâ unius vicis <hi>(Fidei)</hi> corruptione, totam Fidem Christianam pessumdarent; &amp; Fidem Christianorum à Christi gratiâ, ad suas ipsoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> virtutes &amp; opera converterent.</note> as wee do the word faith, in this point of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification, is to overthrow the faith &amp; Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36398:25"/> that in<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Philippus Melancton in Epitome renovarae Doctrinae Ecclesiasticae, tom. 2. operum pag. 4.</hi> Nec in Poenitentia, nec in justificatione requirunt Spiritum Sanctum; sed rationis conatu contenti sunt, qui tamen nihil aliud, nisi mera Hypocrisis est.</note> Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Repentance, wee cōtent our selves with humane force, rejecting the assistance of the holy Ghost; that<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Guilielmus Bucamus loco 31. de Justificat. paragr. 48. pag. 356.</hi> Christi meritis diffisi, confugiunt ad merita bonorum operum &amp; fuffragia Sanctorum.</note> through distrust of the Merrits of Jesus-Christ, wee have recours to the Meritts of our worcks, &amp; to the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages of the Saints; that<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico orthodoxe, seu summâ Controvers. quaest. 1. Prooemiali de Haeresibus tom. 1. pag. 39.</hi> Pelagiani docebant hominem justum in hac vitâ nullum omninò hebere peccatum, &amp;c. Tales &amp; similes Haereses in Papatu vigent: omnes docent posse hominem in hac vita perfecte legem implere, unde sequitur eum esse sine peccato. <hi>Franciscus Burmanus in Synopsi Theologica l. 6. c. 7. paragr. 20. tom. 2. pag. 232.</hi> Adoptarum Pontificii Pelagianorum impeccantiam, dùm regenitos omni peccato mortali, omnique malo habitu carere posse contendunt, ac in Synodo Tridentina Iustos in omni opere venialiter, nedum mortaliter peccare negant, quam sententiam sine manifesta hypocrisi, &amp; divinae L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>gis violatione tueri non possunt.</note> wee adopt the Error of the Pelagians concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Impeccability of the Iust, or that the Iust sin not; that<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ioannes Calvinus l. 4. Institut. c. 15.</hi> §. <hi>10. pag. 351.</hi> Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>spicuum est quàm falsum sit, quod docuerunt pridem nonnulli, in quo alii persistunt, per Baptismum solvi nos &amp; eximi ab originali peccato, &amp; à corruptione, quae ab Adam in universam posteritatem propagata est, atque in eamdem justitiam naturaeque puritatem restitui, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>quam abtinuisset Adam, si in ea, in quá primùm creatus fuerat, naturae integritata stetisset.</note> wee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36398:26"/> wee teach, that Baptisme gives us the same degree of sanctity, that Adam had, if he had Remain'd in the state of Inocence; that<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Theodorus Beza in Antithesi Papatus &amp; Christianismi tract. Theologic. c. 7. tom. 1. pag. 63.</hi> Romani originis peccatum levi aquae aspergine, volunt statim ac penitùs in nobis elui, &amp; ejus reliquias docent peccati rationem non habere, nisi consensus accedat, quam Doctrinam prorsùs diabolicam esse affirmamus. <hi>Hieronymus Zanchius operum Theologicorum Vol. 1. tom. 4. Edit Gamoneti anni 1605. pag. 71. l. 1. de peccato Originali cap. 5. thesi 3. de Concupiscentia in renatis.</hi> Non potest negligi haec Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia, quin negligatur gloria Christi, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ergo si nobis cordi est gloria Christi &amp; salus nostra non debemus permittere, ut Pontificia sententia obtineat in Ecclesia; sed pro viribus expug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanda est. <hi>Ioannes Heydeggerus in Anatome Conc. Trid. ad sess. 5. de Peccato Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nali. tom. 1. pag. 131.</hi> Totum dogma de expunctione Peccati Originalis per Baptismum, ad avaritiae &amp; suberbiae incudem formatum est. Id enim dant operam Clerici, ut Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum, qua ab ipsis conferuntur, excollatur efficacia, &amp; indè ministerio suo lucrum ac honos accrescat.</note> our doctrine, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which original sin, is taken away by Baptisme, is diabolicall; that it would be to the honnour &amp; glory of IESUS-CHRIST, &amp; of salvation not to suffer it, &amp; that it was forged upon the anvile of Coveteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, &amp; of the ambition of the Eclesiasticks, for to rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se the Efficacie of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments they administer, &amp; for to augment the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; Revenues of their Ministry;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:36398:26"/> that<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Charles Drelincourt Minister of Charenton in his Abridgement of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies c. 72. pag. 300. of the Edition, of the year 1674.</hi> The Roman Church teacheth that Concupiscence Remains after Baptisme: by which the Roman Church Confesseth that the sin Remains after Baptisme, <hi>Thesaurus Disput. Sedan. th. 53. de Baptismo parte 3. tom. 1. pag 787.</hi> Apostolum Tridentini Patres ausi sunt accusare oscitantiae &amp; locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis impropriae &amp; non verae dicentes Apostolum concupiscentiam appellasse peccatum, non quod verè &amp; propriè peccatum esset in renatis, <hi>&amp;c. Joannes Heydeggerus loco mox laudato. tom. 1. pag. 131.</hi> Viderit Synodus Tridentina, an non Scripturam sacram Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themate, nefariè ac veluti <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> perculserit.</note> wee fall into Contradiction, saying that the Concupiscence is not (to speake properly) à sinn in the Regenerated; and that it is to accuse the Apostle not to have thought of what he writt, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Anathema to the holy scripture, &amp; comitt à kind of a deicide: that<note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Philippus Meloncton in Epitome renovatae Doctrinae Ecclesiasticae tom. 2. pag. 4.</hi> Aristotelici Theologi docent mereri nos nostris viribus &amp; nostro conatu gratiam. <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister Noguier, in his answer to the Exposition of the doctrine of the Church by my Lord, the Bishop of Meaux, then Bishop of Comdom 1. part. c. 12. pag. 103.</hi> My lord of comdom, doth he not give to understand, that he approves of all that the schoole of Rome holds &amp; Maintains, that if man by his free will, cannot do works which Merrit Eternall life, he may have movements which disposes him to receave grace, which in their Langua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ge is caled Merit of congruity. The seacond answer to the same worke of the Bishop of Comdom, by à Nameless author pag. <hi>85.</hi> The Councill of Trent teacheth that of our selves, wee prepare our selves, and wee dispose our selves to grace, by which wee are Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated. <hi>Franciscus Burmannus in Synopsi Theolog. l. 6. 8.</hi> §. <hi>25. tom. 2. pag. 241.</hi> In eo errant Pontificii, quod meritum operibus ante gratiam factis tribuunt. <hi>Jurieu in his book intituled à preservatif. p. 150. art. 7.</hi> The Councill of Trent by her Ambiguitys &amp; Rambling expressions, has left semipelagianisme, &amp; even Pelagianisme in their intire profession.</note> according to our Doctrine,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36398:27"/> of our selves, wee prepare our selves for graee, &amp; that wee merrit it by our works which precede it, as the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians believed; &amp; that the councill of Trent has confirm'd semipelagianis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, &amp; even Pelagianisme, in every point; that<note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Philippus Melancton, in Commentar, ad cap. 3. Epist ad Romanos tom 3. operum pag. 953.</hi> Tantùm tribuunt Christo, quod principium &amp; occasionem merendi nobis promeruerit, ipsi sic loquuntur Christum meruisse primam gratiam, posteà sepeliunt eum &amp; fingunt otiosum esse, &amp; imaginantur homines meriti remissionem peccatorum &amp; justo esse propter propriam impletionem Legis.</note> JESUS-CHRIST, is to yow but an occasiō to merrit; &amp; that after he has merited for us the first grace, wee believe, that he is of no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re use to us, and that wee alone merrit the Remission of our sins; that<note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus Disputat. Sedanens. th. 5. de Fide justificante</hi> &amp; <hi>operibus parte 3. tom. 1. pag. 637.</hi> An quidquam est Evangelio magis adversum, aut Religionis Christianae magis Fundamenta convellens, quàm haec Doctrina, quae docet hominem praeditum Fide justificante posse damnari.</note> wee teach, that à man may be damn'd, haveing à Iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieing faith; that<note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Guillielmus Bucamus loco 31. de Justificatione §. 48. pag. 356.</hi> Error Pontificiorum <hi>9.</hi> Mariae Virgini autoritatem justificandi tribuunt; Papae potestatem venden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di remissionem peccatorum.</note> wee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36398:27"/> give or atribute to the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, the power to Iustifie us, &amp; to the Pope the power to sell the Remission of sins; that<note n="(n)" place="bottom">Ioannes Heydeggerus in Anatome Concilii Tridentini, tom. 1. pag. 261. <hi>Quid statuendum de hac fastuosa Doctrina,</hi> nostram Doctrinam de meritis operum intelligit. The author of the Considerations upon the Circular letters, &amp; Pastorall advertisement of the Clergie of France to those of the Pretended Reformed Religion, consideration the fourth pag. 111. <hi>The thought of Meritt is of it selfe à thought of Pride. Essentially Contrary to true Godlynesse.</hi> Iurieu in the preservatiff pag. 149. <hi>Wherfore have wee so much Iealousies against this word Merritt, which is superbe &amp; opposiit to Christian Humility.</hi> Ioannes Heydeggerus ad sess. 6. Conc. Trident. tom. 1. pag. 131. <hi>Ipsos Pharisaeos Romanenses, suffarcinatos persuasione propriae justitiae.</hi>
                           </note> our opinion of Merrit is full of Contempt &amp; pride, Essentially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to true piety; &amp; that wee are Pharises stuffed with the persuasion of our one Righteousness, for that wee ought to believe according to the divinity of the Pretended Reformed, that all the best works of the Iust, meritt but Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damination.<note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Udalricus Zuinglius in explanatione Articulorum seu Propositionum suarum art. 20. tom. 1. operum fol. 46.</hi> Neque ullum opus existimandum est ut meritum, sed hoc cogitandum potius, omnia nostra opera nihil mereri, quàm damnationem.</note>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36398:29"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>ARTICLE IV.</hi> Of the adoration of JESUS-CHRIST in the Euchariste, &amp; of the Mass.</head>
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="continuation">
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Professio Fidei:</hi> Profiteor pariter in Missa eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rri Deo verum. proprium &amp; propitiatorium Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium pro vivis &amp; defunctis.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2. Conc. Trid. sess. 22. cap. 1.</hi> Sacrificium, quo cruentum illud se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel in cruce per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agendum repraesen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taretur, ejusque memoria in finem usque saeculi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maneret, atque
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36398:29"/> illius salutaris vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in remissionem eorum, quae à nobis quotidie commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur, peccatorum applicaretur.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Professio Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei:</hi> Atque in san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctissimo Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiae Sacramento esse verè realiter &amp; substantialiter corpus &amp; sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem unâ cum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ &amp; Divinitate Domini nostri Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su Christi: fierique conversionem totius substantiae panis in corpus &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36398:30"/> substantiae vini in sanguinem, quam conversionem Catholica Ecclesia transsubstantiatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem appellat: fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor etiam sub alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra tantùm specie, totum atque inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum Christum, verumque Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum sumi.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Conc. Trid. sess. 13. Can. 6.</hi> Si quis dixerit in Eucharistiae Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento Christum unigenitum Filium Dei, non esse cultu latriae etiam exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no adorandum &amp;c.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36398:30"/> Idololatras, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema sit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="continuation">
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36398:29"/>
                        <head>DOCTRINE OF THE CHURCH.</head>
                        <p>I 1. Confess that in the holy mass, is offerr'd to God, one true, proper, &amp; propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory Sacrifice for the liveing, &amp; for the dead.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. A Sacrifice which Represents unto us the Bloody Sacrifice of JESUS-CHRIST upon the Cross, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serveing in us the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory therof, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys unto us, a whole some virtue for the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36398:29"/> Remission of the sin̄s wee dayly comit.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. I believe that the body &amp; Blood with the soul and Divinity of JESUS-CHRIST are truly, really &amp; substa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ntially Contein'd in the most holy Sacrament of the Euchariste; &amp; that there is made a Changement of the whole substance of bread in to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; of the whole substance of the wine,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36398:30"/> into the Blood; is that which the Catholick Church calls Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation. I confess, that in each of both kinds, is receaved the whole body &amp; blood of JESUS-CHRIST &amp; the true Sacrament.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. If any one shall say that JESUS-CHRIST only son of God, ought not to be adored in the holy Sacrament of the Euchariste, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worship, even Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriourly, &amp; that tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se, that adore him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36398:30"/> are Jdolaters, let him be Anathema.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="calumnies">
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:36398:29"/>
                        <head>CALUMNIES OF THE PRETENDED REFORMED.</head>
                        <p>THat<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus Disputat. Sedan. de Sacramento Eucharistiae parte. 2. th. 40. tom. 1. pag. 810.</hi> Tenentur violatae Religionis &amp; depravati Evangelii, qui nobis ex humano ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebro procuderunt novum Sacerdotium cujus Christus non est Autor, <hi>&amp;c. Et in thesi 12. de Missa &amp; Transsubstantione pag. 825. ejusdem tom. 1.</hi> Tenetur Ecclesia Romana vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latae Religionis, quae novum Sacerdotium &amp; Sacrificium instituerit, absque ullo Dei man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dato, per Sacrificium Sacrificulus Christo anteponitur.</note> wee have forged a new Preist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, of which JESUS-CHRIST is not the author, &amp; an other sacrifice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that of his death, in which wee place the Preist above JESUS-CHRIST; that<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ibidem th. 34. pag. 828.</hi> Eo procedit superstitio, ut Sacerdos dicat se Christum offere Deo in honorem Sanctorum, quae oratio Sanctos supra Christum evehit.</note> in the sacrifice of the Mass, wee Raise the Saints in Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teing their memoires a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove JESUS-CHRIST
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36398:29"/> that<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Catechismus Heydelbergensis quaest. 80. referente &amp; laudante Francisco Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manno in Synopsi Theologica l. 7. c. 15. §. 31. tom. 2 pag. 414.</hi> Missae Sacrificium nihil aliud est, quam abnegatio unici illius Sacrificii &amp; Passionis Iesu Christi &amp; execranda Idololatria. <hi>Addit ipse Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>mannus.</hi> Specie enim sacrificii Christi, Patri quotidiè offerendi, excogitatum hic fuit diaboli astu sacrificium falsum &amp; idololatricum, unicè comparatum ad abolendum verum Christi sacrificium &amp; extirpandam omnem ejus vim &amp; memoriam. <hi>Joan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes VVollebius Theologiae Professor Basileensis in compendio Doctrinae Christianae l. 1. c. 18. §. 22. pag. 103. Edit. Amstelodamensis an. 1655.</hi> Evertunt eamdem Christi satisfactionem Papani, alios Sacerdotes constituentes, &amp; Missam Idololatricam pro sacrificio obtrudentes.</note> the Sacrifice of the Mass is a renounce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to that of the Cross; &amp; to the fruit of the death &amp; Passion of JESUS-CHRIST; that it destroys &amp; overthrows it by a sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Attempt; that<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Guilielmus Bucanus loco 48. §. 145, pag. 798.</hi> Pontificiorum errores, qui Missae nomen à sacris Isiais sunt mutuati, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Verba coenae Dominicae, in Ephesias Litteras transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, seu in consecrationem talem quae nihil dissert ab incantationibus magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>is, <hi>&amp;c. pag. 799. Ibidem</hi> Qua ratione sacrificium Crucis Christi prorsùs evacuatur, unicum &amp; perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum ejus Sacerdotium negatur, mortis ejus meritum obruitur, Chrstus rursus occiditur. <hi>Synopsis purioris Theologiae Professorum Lugdunensium apud Batavos disp. 46. th. 1. pag. 698.</hi> Pontificii loco Coenae à Christo institutae, nobis Missam obtrudunt; haec Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum impietatis, signum Apostasiae, ac vinculum dissentionis appellari potest.</note> wee have borrowed the name of Mass from the sacrifices of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desse Isis; &amp; that in this Sacrifice, wee put JESUS-CHRIST agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to Death; that the Consecration which wee do
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36398:30"/> differs nothing from the enchantments of Magick; &amp; that one may call the Mass the Sacrament of ungodlinesse, the signe of Apostasie; &amp; the chaine of dissention; that<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Guilielmus Bucanus loco mox laud. pag. 800.</hi> Scenico &amp; histrionico ornatu, gestu, beatu, murmure, sibilis, gemitibus, cantu &amp; aliis modis, tanquàm Orgia Sacra &amp; Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanalia celebrant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </note> wee celebrate the Mass like the orgies &amp; the Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanalias or feasts of the Pagans; that<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Georgius Dounamus in libro cui titulus est</hi> Papa Antichristus, l. <hi>3. c. 7. pag. 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</hi> Missas etiam celebrant, hoc est Christum ipsum Deo offerunt, in honorem Sanctorum, pro illorum intercessione apud Deum obtinenda.</note> in the Mass wee offer JESUS-CHRIST to God in the hōnour of the Saints, for to obteine by him their intercession with God; that<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Franciscus Burmannus in Synopsi Theologica l. 7. c. 15. §. 25. tom. 2. pag. 412.</hi> Sacramentum hoc in Idolum in Ecclesia erexerunt, qui summus erroris gradus est, ita ut panis ipsorum ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>num sit, cùm non manducetur solùm; sed &amp; adoretur. <hi>Et §. 28. ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem pag.</hi> Nos autem h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>c pacto Sacrilegio &amp; Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>latriâ contaminari Ecclesiam, Deumque novum invehi, &amp; furfura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>um denique numen coli contendimus. <hi>Theodorus Beza in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thesi Paparus &amp; Christianissimi tom. 1. tractat. Theologic. pag. 64.</hi> Ita fit ut miseri Papistae, ex ipsorum placitis vel sint Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>lolatrae, panis enim adorationem, vel ipsi quidem non inficiabuntur esse Id l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>iam, vel non nisi sub conditione, si fortè a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>fa rit▪ furf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>raceum illud suum numen possint adorare. <hi>Franciscus Burmannus mox laudatus eodem l. &amp; capite, §. 29. pag. 413. tom. 2.</hi> Adorant aliquid, quod Christus non est; sed Idolum.</note> wee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:36398:30"/> adore a God of meale; that<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Georgius Dounamus in L. cui titulus est:</hi> Papa Antichristus, l <hi>3. c. 6. pag. 180.</hi> Sicut Nestoriani Christum Hominem adorant, non quod Deus sit; sed quia Deo conjunctus; atque ita creaturam pro Creatore adorant; sic Pontificii latriae cultum, qui soli Deo debetur Sacramento Eucharistiae exibent, non quod Deus sit; sed quod Deum in eo adesse credant. <hi>Joannes Calvinus in Epist. ad D. N. S. D. pag. 95. secundae Partis Voluminis Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum ult. Edit. Amstelodam.</hi> Quam bellè Missae conveniat cum Coena Domini &amp;c. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus autem abominationis, ipsa, quae ibi primas tenet, elementi adoratio est.</note> wee renew the Error of the nestorians, adoreing for JESUS-CHRIST that which is not Iesus-Christ, but a bit of Bread.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>
                        <hi>ARTICLE THE V.</hi> Of satisfaction, of Purgatorie, and of Jndulgencies.</head>
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="continuation">
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Conc. Trid. sess. 14. cap. 8.</hi> Quoad satisfactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem sancta Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus declarat falsum omninò esse &amp; à verbo Dei alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36398:31"/> culpam à Domino nunquàm remitti, quin uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versa etiam poena condon etur.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Ibidem</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que verò ita nostra est satisfactio haec quam pro peccatis nostris exsolvimus, ut non sit per Christum Iesum; nam qui ex no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, tanquàm
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36398:31"/> ex nobis nihil pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumus, eo cooperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, qui nos confortat omnia possumus, ita non habet homo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè glorietur: sed omnis gloriatio no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra in Christo est, in quo vivimus, in quo meremur, in quo satisfacimus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientes fructus dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos poenitentiae, qui ex illo vim habent, ab illo efferuntur Patri, &amp; per illum acceptantur à Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="44" facs="tcp:36398:32"/>
                           <hi>1. Professio Fidei:</hi> Constanter teneo Purgatorium esse, animasque ibi detentas Fidelium suffragiis adjuvari.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:36398:32"/>
                           <hi>1. Conc. Trid. sess. 25. in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto de Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio:</hi> Praecipit S. Synodus Episcopis, ut sanam de Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorio Doctrinam à sanctis Patribus &amp; sacris Conciliis traditam à Christi fidelibus teneri, doceri, &amp; ubique praedicari diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter studeant.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="46" facs="tcp:36398:33"/>
                           <hi>1. Professio Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei:</hi> Indulgentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum etiam potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem à Christo in Ecclesia relictam fuisse.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2. Conc. Trid. sess. 25. in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto de Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiis.</hi> Atque hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jusmodi potestate divinitùs sibi tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita, antiquissimis etiam temporibus Ecclesia usa fuerit.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <hi>3. Professio Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei:</hi> Illarumque usum Christiano populo maximè sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutarem affirmo.</p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <hi>4. Conc. Trid. in eodem Decreto de Indulg.</hi> In his tamen contedendis, moderationem juxta vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem &amp; probatam in Ecclesia consuetudinem adhiberi cupit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="continuation">
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:36398:30"/>
                        <head>DOCTRINE OF THE CHURCH.</head>
                        <p>AS to satisfaction, the holy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill declares, that it is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36398:31"/> entirely falls and farr from the word of God, to say that the sin is never forgiven by our Lord, but the paine due for the same is also Remitted.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. But this satisfaction by which wee pay for our sins, is not so much ours, as it is done and accomplished by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36398:31"/> JESUS-CHRIST for wee, of our selves, in as much as of us, can do nothing, but wee can do all with the assistance of him that strengthneth us, So that man has nothing wherin he may glorifie; but all the subiect of our glory is in JESUS-CHRIST, in whom wee live, in whom wee merit, &amp; in whom wee make satisfaction, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king true fruits of Repentance, which have their force and their meritt from him,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36398:32"/> and which are offer'd by him to the father, &amp; by his intermission they are receaved &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the father.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. I firmly hold, that there is a Purgatorie, and that the souls of the faithfull, which are the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re detain'd, are helped by the suffrages &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers of the faithfull.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:36398:32"/>1. The holy Councill of Trent gives orders to Bishops, that they may have a particular care, that the faith &amp; beliefe of the faithfull, touching purgatorie, may be Conformable to the holy doctrine which was left unto us by the holy fathers, &amp; by the Councills, &amp; that it may be every where preached unto them &amp; taught after the same manner.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <pb n="46" facs="tcp:36398:33"/>1. I hold that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Indulgencies, was left by JESUS-CHRIST to the Church.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. That she has used them since the primiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve times.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. That there use is most wholsome to the Christian People.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. And that according to the desire of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly councill, they ought to be granted with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, according to the antient &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Custome in the Church.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="calumnies">
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:36398:30"/>
                        <head>CALUMNIES OF THE PRETENDED REFORMED.</head>
                        <p>THat<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Franciscus Burmannus in Synopsi Theologica, l. 6. c. 9. §. 38. tom 2. pag. 258.</hi> Satisfactio merum est figmentum infandae superbiae plenum &amp; Christi Redemptioni adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum. <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 6. de Satisfactionibus tom. 1. pag. 595.</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vissima omnium satisfactio illa est, quam Purgatorium vocant, voce quidem barbara; sed sensu magis incongruo &amp; in Christum contumelioso. <hi>Synopsis purioris Theologiae disputat. 39. thesi 21. pag. 545.</hi> Aliquas esse satisfactiones pro peccato praeter satisfactionem Christi, dogma absurdum &amp; blasphemum est.</note> our Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Concerning satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction &amp; Purgatorie is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:36398:31"/> full of vanity &amp; pride, and injurious to Iesus-Christ; that it<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 7. de Satisfact. tom. 1. pag. 595.</hi> Cùm pro tota poena Christus abundè satisfecerit, alienum planè est à justitia Dei, pro uno eodem que debito geminam exigere solutionem. <hi>Ioannes Calvinus l. 3. Institut. c. 5. paragr. 6. pag. 175.</hi> Clamandum non modo votis, sed gutturis ac laterum contentione Purgatorium exitiale Sathanae esse commentum, quod Christi crucem evacuat, quod contumiliam Dei misericordiae non ferendam irrogat, &amp;c. Superest Purgatorium meram esse eamque horribilem in Christum blasphemiam. <hi>The Confession of faith of the Pretended Reformed of France art, 24.</hi> wee hold Purgatorie to be an Illusion proceeding from the shop of the Divill.</note> makes God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just, &amp; that it is an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion proceeding from the shop of sathan; that<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Joannes Calvinus ubi mox suprà. Thesaurus disputat Sedan. th. 5. de Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factionibus tom. 1. pag. 595.</hi> Iejunia, peregrinationes, mulctas pecuniarias sub obtentis Paenitentiae, &amp; flagellationis laconicae <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>, Imitamentum vocant opera satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoria, his tricis putant Deo satisfieri pro poena temporali. <hi>Et thesi 16. pag. 597.</hi> Praesto est perfectissima Christi satisfactio, cui adjungere sublasta quaedam opera, gerrasque sicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, flagellationem &amp; ciborum distinctionem, tùm incubare solo &amp; cranium habere pro cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicali, &amp; sub interula modo succingi, qui lumbo exulceret, cedit in Christi contumeliam. <hi>Mox:</hi> Sanè haec ad Lydium Verbi Dei lapidem explorata, tantùm abest ut satisfaciant Deo, ut etiam poenam mereantur, &amp; ad lancem judicii divini ponderata, immensum quantùm peccata novo pondere pragravent.</note> all the fasts &amp; all the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications of the flesh, do but cover Iesus-Christ with affronts; &amp; that far from being able to employ them to please God, they load us with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:36398:31"/> new crimes; that<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ibidem th. 24. pag. 598.</hi> Nititur hoc dogma illo axiomate, quo vix ulla est capita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lior Doctrina, Christum morte sua nos liberasse à poenà &amp; culpâ peccatorum, quae antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Baptismum; at pro poenis peccatorum, quae fiunt post Baptismum, Christum aut non satisfecisse, aut satisfactionem ejus nobis non imputari. <hi>Ioannes Calvinus l. 3. Institut. c. 5. paragr. 2. pag. 574.</hi> Quí poterat foedius profanari Christi Sanguis, quàm dùm nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur sufficere ad peccatorum remissionem, ad reconciliationem, ad satisfactionem, nisi velut arescentis &amp; exhausti defectus aliundè suppleatur &amp; sufficiatur.</note> our doctrine concerning fatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, is grounded upon this that IESUS-CHRIST has not made satisfaction, but for the sin comitted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore baptisme; &amp; denies the sufficiency of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world; that<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Philippus Melancton in respons. ad articulos Bavaricos, ad art. 19. tom. 1. operum fol. 367</hi> Apparet hos ritus <hi>(satisfactionum)</hi> à vetustate Ethnica sumptos fuisse: nam apud Ethnicos homicidae gerebant signa reatus, ut agnoscerentur ab aliis &amp; vitarentur tamquàm pollu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>i, nec cum eis mensae &amp; convictus societas esset, ut Orestes queritur se vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum esse, nec receptum ad aliorum mensas. <hi>Ioannes Calvinus l. 3. Institut. c. 5. paragr. 6. pag. 575.</hi> Cum ex multis blasphemiis Purgatorium constructum sit &amp; novis quotidie fulciatur.</note> the begining of our satisfactions proceeds from the customes of Pagans, &amp; that it is not upheld, but by many Blasphemies; that<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedan. th. 9. de satisfactionibus, tom. 1. pag. 600.</hi> Hane compensationem Pontificii dicunt, fieri ex condigno, id est, per aequipollentiam. <hi>Theodorus Beza in Antithesi Papatus &amp; Christianismi tract. Thologic. tom. 1. pag. 61.</hi> Putarunt Papistae se posse quadam compensatione satisfacere divinae justitiae, quâ in re planè ac perspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuè, se potius stupidos simul ac intolerabili arrogantiâ praeditos declararunt.</note> wee maintaine, that by our satisfactions, wee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:36398:32"/> pay God with an equall value; that<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedan. th. 26. de Satisfact. tom. 1. pag. 598.</hi> Hoc est cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tissimum au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>upium per quod ipsa mors Pontificii vectigalis est. estque jam ab aliquot saeculis lucrosa haec nundinatio. <hi>Uldaricus Zuinglius in respons. ad Valentinum tom. 1. operum fol. 263.</hi> Impiorum Sacerdotum avaritia, Christi clarissima verba in alienum sensum violenter detorsit, ut Purgatorium suum, quo non alius quaeslus illis fuit uberior, possent deffendere, quibus in conficta majorum nostrorum miseria, luxus &amp; libidinis suae alimentum, &amp; gaudii laetitiaeque occasionem, quaerere licuit. <hi>Ioannes Calvinus in Antidoto Conc. Trid. ad can, 30. sess. 6. opuscus. pag. 253.</hi> Nisi forte instar Vaticinii accipi volunt suum de Purgatorio commentum, quod à ventriloquis procedit, Nullum enim est, quod ad refarciendos eorum ventres, aeque valeat. <hi>Theodorus Beza in Antithesi Papatus &amp; Christianismi in tract Theolog. tom. 1. pag, 58.</hi> Ignis Purgatorius ad purgandas potiùs crumenas, quàm anin as exstructus est <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. tom. 2. pag. 350. th. 4. de commentitiis peccati poenis, &amp;c.</hi> Ad fastum &amp; quaestum excogitatas esse poenas Purgatorii, ad quastum, siquidem animae hujus ignis terrore perculsae, sacrificulis absorbendas ettam aedes tradiderunt, ut ab hisce cruciatibus immunitatem obtinerent, ideò curam suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giorum pro defunctis persolvendorum sollicite imperant. <hi>Burnet in his Remarks upon the acts of the last generall Assembly of the Clergie of France:</hi> The Church of Rome has gain'd more by Purgatorie, then spain has done by the discovery of the new world.</note> Purgatorie is an invention to get mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; that according our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, the Pope draws tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute from the dead; that<note n="(h)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 22. de Satisfact. humanis tom. 1. pag. 598. <hi>Papalibus Indulgentiis vis tribuitur</hi> (eruendi à flammis Purgatorii) <hi>quae Christo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur.</hi>
                           </note> wee give to Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies the power to Redeem souls from Purgatorie, which wee Refuse to Iesus-Christ; that<note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Idem Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 58. de Satisfact. parte 2. tom. 1. pag. 612.</hi> Gravissimum est quod per impium hoc dogma Deus detruditur solio, &amp; Papa supra Deum extollitur: oportet major sit Deo, qui liberat hominem necessitate parendi Dei mandatis <hi>Peter du Moulin, Minister of Charenton, in his Buckler of faith sect. 89. Edit. of Geneva of the year 1660. pag. 344.</hi> The Pope would have us believe that he Redeems from Purgatorie; in which he manifestly puts himselfe above God.</note> by this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine the Pope deposeth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:36398:32"/> God of his throne, and Raiseth himselfe above him; that<note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 13. de Satisfact. parte 2. tom. 1. pag. 612.</hi> Portenta haec sunt <hi>(Indulgentiae)</hi> &amp; nova dogmata conflata ad incudem avaritiae. His artibus Religio Christiana vertitur in foedam caupanationem. <hi>Et antea th. 19 de Satisfact. parte 1. tom. 1. pag. 602.</hi> Ad calcem Bullae: Datum Romae; cùm potiùs scribendum fuisset venditum Romae. <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico Orthodoxo, seu summa Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. tractat. 3. quaest. 13. §. 8. tom. 2. pag. 97.</hi> Quamvis Indulgentiariis vendendi verbum displicere videatur, nihil tamen aliud intelligunt per causas justas, sine quibus Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiae nullius sunt fructus. <hi>Ibidem vocat eas:</hi> Fictas Indulgentias.</note> the Pope sells Jndulgences, &amp; dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves a shamefull trade on't; that<note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Peter du Moulin in Hyperaspiste l. 1. c. 40. pag. 300. Edit Genevens. an 1636.</hi> Papa indulget &amp; remittit peccata Deo invito, &amp; hanc Papae Indulgentiam valere &amp; ratam esse, quamquàm Deo, non probante piè credendum est. Prefecto hi homines suis absolutionibus &amp; Indulgentiis se suprà Deum efferunt; sedent enim judices in Dei causà.</note> wee believe, that the Pope forgives sins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the will of God; &amp; that, the Indulgencies which he grants are effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious, although God do not approve them; that by<note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Joannes Calvinus Institut. l. 3. c. 5. §. 5. pag. 175.</hi> Porrò ut tales abominatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes praetereamus, quis docuit Papam plumbo &amp; membranâ, gratiam Iesu-Christi includere.</note> Indulgences the Pope Binds the grace of JESUS CHRIST to parchment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:36398:33"/> and lead; that<note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Idem Joannes Calvinus in Epistola adversus Pseudo Nicodemitas opusculo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pag. 414.</hi> Quid diplomata illa quorum te gratiam appetere simulas? An non edita voce clamant, ut nummis relictis, plenas anathemate, atque omni execratione dignas Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentias tibi auferas, &amp;c. atqui eorum latebras si excussertis, nusquàm prolixius, quàm illic Christum irriaeri cum sua cruce reperies.</note> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more to the derision of the cross of JESUS-CHRIST, then Indulgences.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="article">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36398:33"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>ARTICLE VI.</hi> Of the Invocation of Saints, of Relicks, &amp; of Images.</head>
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="continuation">
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Conc. Trid. sess. 25. Decreto de Invocat. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</hi> Sanctos una cum Christo reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes, orationes suas pro hominibus Deo offerre bonum atque utile esse suppliciter cos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocare, &amp; ob bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia impetranda à Deo per Filium ejus Iesum Christum,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36398:34"/> Dominum nostrum, qui solus noster Redemptor &amp; Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator est ad eorum orationes, opem, auxiliumque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugere: illos verò qui negant Sanctos aeterna felicitate in coelo fruentes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocandos esse, aut qui asserunt vel illos pro hominibus non orare, vel eorum, ut pro nobis etiam singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis orent, invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem esse ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latriam,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36398:34"/> vel pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cum verbo Dei, adversarique hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> unius mediatoris Dei &amp; hominum Iesu Christi, vel stultum esse in coelo regnantibus, voce vel mente suplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, impiè sentire. Sanctorum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Martyrum &amp;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36398:35"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="49" facs="tcp:36398:35"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="50" facs="tcp:36398:36"/> aliorum etiam cum Christo viventium sancta corpora quae viva membra fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt Christi, &amp; templum Spiritus sancti ab ipso ad aeternam vitam sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citanda, &amp; glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canda à fidelibus veneranda esse.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Professio Fidei:</hi> Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sanctos unâ
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36398:36"/> cum Christo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnantes veneran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, atque invocan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos esse, eosque orationes Deo pro nobis offerre; atque eorum reliquias esse venerandas.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1. Idem. Conc. Trident. Ibid.</hi> Imagines porrò Christi, Deiparae Virginis &amp; aliorum Sanctorum in Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis praesertim, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendas
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36398:37"/> &amp; retinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, eisque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum honorem &amp; reverentiam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertiendam, non quod credatur inesse aliqua in tis divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas vel virtus propter quam sint colendae, vel quod ab eis sit aliquid p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tendum, vel quod fiducia in imagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus sit fidenda, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti olim fiebat à gentibus, quae in Idolis spem suam collocabant, sed quoniam honos qui eis exhibetur, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur ad prototypa,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36398:37"/>
                           <hi>Professio Fidei:</hi> Firmissimè assero Imagines Christi ac Deiparae semper Virginis, necnon aliorum Sanctor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum habendas &amp; retinendas esse, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que eis debitum honorem ac reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentiam impertien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="continuation">
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36398:33"/>
                        <head>DOCTRINE OF THE CHURCH.</head>
                        <p>THe holy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill teacheth, that the Saints, who Reigne with JESUS-CHRIST, offer prayers to God for men; that it is a good &amp; profitable thing to invocate them,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36398:34"/> &amp; to humbly supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, &amp; to have recours to their assistance, for to obteine graces &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of God by his son, who is our onely Redeemer, &amp; our sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; &amp; that those who denie that the Saints, who enioye in heaven an Eternall felicity, are to be invocated;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36398:34"/> or who hold, that the Saints do not pray to God for men; or that 'tis Idolatry to invocate them, to the end that they should pray even for every one of us in particular; or that it is a thing which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the word of God,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36398:36"/> &amp; that 'tis against the honnour due to JESUS-CHRIST, alone &amp; only Mediator between God &amp; Men; or even that 'tis a miere folly to pray by word, or thought to the Saints who Reign in heaven, have oppinions contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to true piety.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. That the faithfull ought likewise to bear
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36398:36"/> Respect to the bodys of holy Martyrs, &amp; of other Saints who live with JESUS-CHRIST; those bodys haveing been heartofore liveing members of JESUS-CHRIST, &amp; the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the holy Ghost, &amp; will one day Resussi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate to Eternall life.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. That wee ought to have and Retaine principally in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the Images of JESUS-CHRIST,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36398:37"/> the virgin Mother of God, &amp; of other saints, &amp; that the honnour and venerations is to be given, which is due unto them; not that wee believe, that there is in them any divinity, or any vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, for which wee ought to give this worship, or that wee should aske any thing of them, or put any trust in them, as the Pagans did who put their hopes in their Idolls; but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36398:37"/> because that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which is done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them is Referr'd to the originals, whom they Represent.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="calumnies">
                        <pb n="47" facs="tcp:36398:33"/>
                        <head>CALUMNIES OF THE PRETENDED REFORMED.</head>
                        <p>THat<note n="(a)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Joannes Calvinus in antidoto ad articulos sacrae Facultatis Theologiae Parisien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis ad art. 13. opusculorum pag. 196.</hi> Cultum Sanctis exhibere sicut solet mundus, profana est supestitio, &amp; quae gentium potius insaniam redolet, quàm E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>clesia Dei conveniat. <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. de Intercessione Sanctorum parte 2. thesi 40, tom. 2. pag. 572.</hi> Non abesse ab Idololatriâ &amp; periculo novos fingendi Deos, Sactorum intercessionem. <hi>Ibidem thesi 33. de cultu Religioso pag. 598.</hi> Frustrâ de nobis conquerentur Pontificii, quod ipsis cultum Idolorum attribuimus <hi>Hieronymus Zanchius operum Theologicor. tom. 4. pag. 504.</hi> Qui invocat animas Sanctorum, qui ex hac vita migrarunt, idololatra est, &amp;c.</note> the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of Saints, which wee believe, is not far from Idolatry; That<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>The Confession of faith of the Pretended Roformed of France, art 24.</hi> wee believe that all that men have Imagined of the in tercession of saints departed, is but abuse &amp; deceit of the Divill, to make men wander from the true forme of prayer. <hi>Ioannes Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldus Anglus l. 1. de Ecclesiae Romanae Idololatriâ, cap. 1. §. 3. pag. 43. Edit. an. 1598</hi> Papistas in invocatione Sanctorum, Reliquiarum cultu, Imaginum veneratione, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestam impietatem, &amp; idololatriam exercere, queruntur nostri <hi>(Protestantes.)</hi>
                           </note> all that wee believe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is but abuse &amp; deceit of the Divill; that<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. ib. 1. de Superstitioso Sanctorum cultu tom. 2. pag. 614.</hi> Transimus ad aliud idololatriae Pontificiorum caput de adoratione Sanctorum, quâ Ethnicorum heroas &amp; Deo acceptos homines inferiore ac relative cultu adorantium supestitionem renovarunt, <hi>Ibidem th. 4.</hi> Renonovatum Ethnicismum ipsis objicimus,</note> wee are to blame to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:36398:34"/> of the Protestants that atribute unto us the worshiping of Idolls, &amp; the renewing of Paganisme, because that this is such; that<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico Orthodoxo seu summâ Controvers. quaest. 1. prooemiali de Haeresibus tom. 1. pag. 32.</hi> Angelici in Angelorum cultu inclinati fuerunt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Papistae omnes, Angelos bonos universos colunt Religioso cultu, &amp; quisque suum Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum custodem religiose colit. <hi>Georgius Dounamus libro cui titulus est,</hi> Papa Antichristus, <hi>l. 3. c. 6. pag. 173.</hi> Angelicorum de colendis Angelis haeresim longe superant.</note> wee renew the heresie of the Angelists, &amp; that wee surpas them by much; that<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico Orthodoxo citata quaest 1. prooemiali de Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibus tom. 1. pag. 32.</hi> Collyridiani Virginem Mariam colebant &amp; adorabant, qui protereà ab Epiphanto inter haereticos nominantur, &amp; Idololatrae appellantur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Papistae haec omnia faciunt.</note> wee renew that of the Collyridiens, who adored the virgin; that<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ioannes Raynoldus l. 1. de Romanae Ecclesiae Idololatria c. 1. §. 13. pag. 63.</hi> Quemadmodum Deus Rex coeli nuncupatur, sic Mariam coeli nominant Reginam, nec eodem solùm Epitheto, quo Iudaei creaturam ornant, praestanttorem quidem, verumtamen creaturam; sed etiam honore pari prosequuntur. <hi>Theodorus Beza in Antithesi Papatus &amp; Christianismi tract. Theologicar. tom. 1. pag. 59.</hi> Papistae abolent Christi intercessio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mariam invocantes, eam Christo ut matrem pupillo anteponunt. <hi>Georgius Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namus l. 3. cui titulus est,</hi> Papa Antichristus. <hi>c. 6. pag. 176</hi> Virginem Dei param tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm Deam quandam &amp; reginam coeli adorant, imò plusquàm Christum ipsum venerantur. <hi>Synopsis purioris Theolog. disput. 19. thesi 20. de Idololatria pag. 222.</hi> Quam Idololatriam in cultu beatae Virginis Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>iae ita conduplicant, ut nihil sive in verbis sive in factis Deo proprium relinquant; imò suprà Christum Deum in aternum benedictum evechant. <hi>Peter du Moulin in his novelty of papisme l. 3 Controvers. 1. c. 12. pag. 544. of the Edition of Sedan. of 1627.</hi> The severall offices which wee give to the saints bears Witness &amp;c, in the Litanies they say saint Peter pray for us; but to the virgin Mary, they do not say saint virgin pray for us, no more then to Iesus-Christ. <hi>Joannes Calvinus Institut. l. 3. c. 20. §. 21. pag. 233.</hi> In uis omnibus Litaniis, Hymnis &amp; Prosis, ubis, Sanctis mortuis, nihil non honoris defertur, nulla fit Christi mentio ubicumque Papismus viget. <hi>Idem Calvinus ibid. paulo an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>è:</hi> Nimii stuporis fuit, nè dicam insaniae, nobis per ipsos <hi>(Sanctos)</hi> accessum <hi>(ad Deum)</hi> sic velle moliri, ut ab illo <hi>(Christo)</hi> abducere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur fine quo nec eis aditus ullus patet. Id autem aliquot saeculis factitatum, quis neget, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dièque ubicumque Papismus vige: factitari? ad conciliandam Dei benevolentiam eorum merita subindè obtruduntur, atque ut plurimum Christo paeterito, per eorum nomina Deus obsecratur, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> Quâ primum perplexitate Christum inhonorant &amp; solius mediatoris titulo spoliant, <hi>Idem Joannes Calvinus sermone 14. in 1 Epist. ad Timotheum. Of the Edition of Geneva of the year 1561. pag. 72.</hi> The Papists have not forged Patrons &amp; advocats according to the Doctrine of the scriptures, but they have made them as if Iesus-Christ, were nothing at all <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wee see as if Iesus-Christ, were quite debarr'd or excluded by them, &amp; that they atribute nothing whatever unto him, if they had said: &amp; also wee pray the saints of heaven, because they are members of the Church as I would pray this man, or that man so I do the saints of heaven, if the Papists had spoke after this maner there had been some modesty in them, but when they imagin their Patrons to the height of heaven, it is to deprive Iesus-Christ of his Office. therfore 'tis an execrable blasphemie, <hi>Idem Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus comment. In Epist. 1. Ioan. cap. 2. v. 1. operum ult. Edit. Amstelodam. pag. 54.</hi> Christum esse avocatum hodie fatentur unum quidem esse ex multis; sed non solum. Qui inter Papistas paulò plus habent verecundiae non negant Christum eminere; sed posteà ingentem comitum turbam illi associant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Dubium itaque non est, quin totidem Christo Idola opponant Papistae, quot sibi patronos comminiscuntur.</note> wee Equal her to God &amp; preferr her to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:36398:34"/> JESUS-CHRIST; that in the prayers which wee make unto her, wee treat her as JESUS-CHRIST; &amp; that wee say no more to her then to JESUS-CHRIST, saint virgin pray for us; that in all the litanies &amp; prose where wee pray to the Saints, wee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:36398:36"/> make no mention of JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS-CHRIST; that when wee have recours to the Saints as to our Patrons, it is to deprive JESUS-CHRIST of his office of Mediator, and that they are so many Idolls, which wee set up against him; that<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. thesi. 6. de cultu unius Dei tom. 1. pag. 256,</hi> Vni Deo cultus Religiosus tribuendus est, hujusque honoris portio nel minima ad creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>am tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ferri, aut cum ea communicari, sine n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>fario scelere non potest, sive alius pro vero Deo colatur; sive cultus inferior aut subordinatus creaturae tribuatur, sive Deus colatur in ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, aut cum imagine &amp; per Imaginem; hec enim omnia lege Dei caventur &amp; communi Idolotriae nomine censentur, <hi>&amp;c. Idid. pag. 280. th. 27. de Imaginibus:</hi> Adoratio Imaginum, quae frequentatur in Ecclesia Romana, planè Religiosa est, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nec id diffitentur Pontificii, quippe qui volunt per Imagines Deum coli mediatè, &amp; in Imaginibus coli Sanctos &amp; in Sanctis Deum. Pag <hi>283.</hi> Profecto non minori scelere Sancti adorantur, quàm aliae creaturae. <hi>Et thesi 1. de superstitioso Sanctorum cultu tom. 2. pag. 614.</hi> Transimus ad aliud Idololatriae Pontificiorum caput, quâ Ethnicorum heroas &amp; Deo acceptos homines in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriore &amp; relativo cultu adorantium superstitionem renovarunt, <hi>&amp;c. Daniel Chamierus Delphinas in Epist. ad Petrum Cottonum Epist, Iesuiticarum parte 1. Edit. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vensis anni 1599. pag. 150.</hi> Demonstrandum est tibi, vel non admitti Idololatriam, cum creaturis tribuitur honos religiosus, vel Sanctos &amp; Imagines non esse creaturas; vel denique vos Sanctis &amp; Imaginibus non tribuere cultum religiosum. <hi>Et mox:</hi> Multa dixisti distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guens ea tria honorum <hi>(latriae, duliae &amp; hyperduliae)</hi> capitâ non ex ipsa eorum interna aliqua differentia; sed tantum de vario gradu earum, quibus is honos defertur.</note> wee believe that one must honour the Saints, their Relicks, &amp; Images, with a Religious worship, of the same nature, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver less, then that which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:36398:36"/> wee give vnto God; that<note n="(h)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. thesi 1. de cultu Religioso. tom. 2. pag. 587. <hi>Pontificios honorem soli Christo debitum Sanctis, quos mediatores constituunt, deferre.</hi>
                           </note> wee take away the quality of Mediator from JESUS-CHRIST, to give it to the Saints; that one cannot<note n="(i)" place="bottom">Ioannes Calvinus in admonitione de reliquis opuscul. pag. 203. Fieri nullo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo potest, quin inde ad Idololatriam homines paulatim declinent, neque enim reliquias intueri, aut attrectare possunt, sine veneratione, in quâ nullus tenetur modus, quin protiùs honor Christo debitus illis tribuatur. Itaque ut paucis dicam reliquia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum desiderium numquàm suprestitione caret, imò quod deterius est mater est Idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latriae.</note> have Relicks without Idolatrie; that<note n="(k)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. in thesi de Reliquiis Sanctorum parte 1. th. 2. tom. 1. pag. 394. <hi>Adorandas esse reliquias Sanctorum summo consensu creditur in Ecclesia Romanâ.</hi>
                           </note> it is the comōn beliefe of the Church of Rome, that one must adore them; that<note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ibidem pag. 267. th. 24. de Imaginibus &amp; Idolis;</hi> Prima controversia est de Imaginibus D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>irca quas Ecclesia Ramana suprà fidem insanit.</note> this Church is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded even to madness to defend &amp; hold for the Images of God; that<note n="(m)" place="bottom">Ibidem pag. 275. th. 2. Circa Imagines Sanctorum Ecclesia Romana supra fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem insanit, quarum in Templis tanta est multitudo, ut possit alter populus lapideus appellari, qui populus inanimis colitur à populo animato.</note> she proposes a people of sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, to be adored by a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing people: that<note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ibidem th. 27. pag. 280.</hi> Adoratio Imaginum, quae frequentatur in Ecclesia Romana planè religiosa est, &amp;c. nec id diffitentur Pontificii.</note> she maketh profession of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:36398:37"/> of adoreing Jmages with à Religious worship; that<note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Ibid. th. 5. pag. 276.</hi> Quibus Imaginibus credi inesse vim aliquam &amp; sanctitatem, quasi virtus aliqua coelestis in eis nidularetur, hinc liquet quod plebs restes suas praecatorias aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>icat pedibus Imaginum, ut sint sanctiores, statuis fingit oscula, cereos accendit.</note> wee believe that à Celestiall virtue Remains in them, that<note n="(p)" place="bottom">Andraeas Rivetus in Catholic. orthodoxo quaest. 1. Prooemiali de haeresib. tom. 1. pag. 32. Georgius Dounamus in lib. cui titulus est: Papa Antichristus l. 3. c. 6. pag. 174. Cum Antropomorphytis, Deo humanam formam affingunt, cùm eum in figura hominis pingunt. &amp;c. pag. 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. cum Armenis illis qui Chazinzarii; vel Stavro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lattae dicti sunt, crucem adorant, ipsoque <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> cultu prosequuntur, &amp;c. cum Basilidianis uttunur Imaginibus, &amp;c. cum Carpocratianis, Imagines Iesu &amp; aliorum colunt adorando, pag. 176. cum Christiano-Cathegoris, Imagines Christi, beatae Mariae Virginis, Angelorum &amp; Sanctorum divino honore prosequuntur, pag. 178. Cum Iacobitis &amp; Armenis. Imagines Patris &amp; Spiritus Sancti effingunt, nec fabricant solùm Imagines, sed adorant &amp; colunt; quâ in re cum crassissimis quibusque Idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latris, non apud Iudaeos modo; sed etiam apud Gentes conferendi.</note> wee Renew all the heresies of the Carpocratiens, Basili diens, staurolatres &amp; others, who kept &amp; adored Images; that<note n="(q)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. th. 14. de Idololatria parte 3. tom. 1. pag, 285. <hi>Si his</hi> (Nicenae secundae Synodi Patribus) <hi>creditur, gravius est crimen non colere Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, quàm negare, Christum esse pro nobis mortuum.</hi>
                           </note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the second Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of Nice, it is a greater Crime not to adore Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, then to deny that Jesus-Christ dyed for us; that by an Idolatrie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:36398:37"/> truly Pagan,<note n="(r)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Daniel Chamierus in Epist. ad Gautierum Jesuitam Epistolar. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>. parte 2. edit. Genevensis anni 1601. pag. 137.</hi> Cur non abscedis ab illo omnium errorum crassissimo errore, quem ut deffendas, nulla suppetunt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, idololatriam dico quâ nullum invenit unquam Diabolus venenum nocentius in orbem, nec ullam unquam tetriorem ea, quae apud vos viget, nominibus tantùm distante ab Ethnicâ, paulumque deflectente ad Christianismum; sed reapse Ioves exhibente, &amp; Mercurios &amp; Minervas, &amp; Martes &amp; Perseos, &amp; Atlantes &amp; Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; Neptunos &amp; Thetydas, &amp; Esculapios &amp; Vulcanos, &amp; reliqua omnia Gentium numina, Minoas etiam &amp; Rhadamentos. <hi>Ericus Rhonaeus in libro cui titulus:</hi> Idea Antichristi reformandi <hi>parte 2. l. 1. c. 12.</hi> Non potest dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimen aliquod inveniri cultus Ethnici &amp; Papistici, ad statuas, nisi quod nomina &amp; titulos tantum mutarunt, hic Iehova, illic Iupiter, hîc Maria, illîc Diana; hîc Catharina, illic Minerva; hîc Paulus, illîc Mercurius. <hi>Daniel Chamierus in Epist. ad Petrum Cottonum Epist. Jesuiticar. parte 1. pag. 46.</hi> Quae enim quaeso illa est Catharina, nisi Idolum fictum ad instar Ethnicae Pallados? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Quis possit negare Christophorum portentum esse? Quis Georgium, Papisticum Persea. <hi>Thesaurus disputat. Sedanens. thesi 24. de Sanctis &amp; eorum cultu parte. 1. tom. 1. pag. 340.</hi> Sancta Margareta in Ecclesia Romana Iunonis Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae locum invasit. <hi>Ibid. th. 25.</hi> Christophorus gygas clavam tenens ad imitationem Herculis Christum dorso bajulans, &amp; in trajectione rapidi fluminis clavâ praeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans viam <hi>th. 26. pag. 341.</hi> de S Georgio Angliae sub Papatu Patrono, mirae sunt, quae narrantur; nulla Idololatria evidentior, nullum figmentum audacius, immò nec nequius.</note> wee propound to the people the worship of Jupiter, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, Minerva, Mars, Perses, Atlas, Venus, Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, Thetis, Esculapes, Vulcain, &amp; the Rest of the heathen Gods; even minos &amp; Rhadamante.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="article">
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:36398:38"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>ARTICLE VII.</hi> Of the Superiority of the Roman Church &amp; of obedience to the Pope.</head>
                     <div xml:lang="lat" type="continuation">
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1 Professio Fidei:</hi> Sanctam Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, &amp; Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam Romanam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiam, omnium Ecclesiarum Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem &amp; Magistram agnosco, Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Pontifici, Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti Petri Apostolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Principis Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessori, ac Iesu Christi Vicario, veram obedientiam spondeo ac juro.</p>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:36398:38"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Conc. Trident. sess. 25. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>format. cap. 2.</hi> praecipit sancta Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodus, Patriarchis, Primatibus, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiscopis, &amp; Episcopis, &amp; omnibus aliis, &amp;c. ut veram obedientiam Summo Romano Pontifici spondeant &amp; profiteantur. <hi>Et in ead sess. decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to de ciborum delect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>:</hi> Sancta Romana Ecclesia omnium Ecclesiarum Mater &amp; Magistra statuit, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="continuation">
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:36398:38"/>
                        <head>DOCTRINE OF THE CHURCH.</head>
                        <p>I 1. Acknowledge the holy Catholick and Apostolick Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, mother &amp; mistriss of all other Churches; and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miss &amp; swear true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Roman Bishop, vicar on Earth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36398:38"/> of JESUS-CHRIST, successor of Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Prince of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:lang="eng" type="calumnies">
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:36398:38"/>
                        <head>CALUMNIES OF THE PRETENDED REFORMED.</head>
                        <p>THat<note n="(a)" place="bottom">Thesaurus disputat. Sedan. th. 13. de summo Controvers. Judice tom. 1. pag. 384. <hi>Ecclesia est supra Scripturam.</hi>
                           </note> wee Raise the Church of Rome aboue the holy Scriptures; that<note n="(b)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Peter du Moulin in Hyperaspiste l. 2. c. 12. pag. 384.</hi> Si ut volunt adversarii; sacrae Scripturae authoritas nititur &amp; fundatur authoritate Ecclesiae; hujus autem Ecclesiae authoritas fundatur in sucessione Papae in Petri Primatum, quae non est Iuris divini; sed humani, nonne inde sequitur Scripturam sacram non esse juris divini, &amp; fundari in humana authoritate, &amp; ad humanas conjecturas &amp; opiniones redigi, quae via compendiosissima est ad Atheismum.</note> the authority of the scripture according to us is grounded upon the Pope; that<note n="(c)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Thesaurus disput. Sedanens. tom. 1. pag. 622. th. 58. de satisfactionibus:</hi> Praecipui quique adversariorum praetendunt, &amp; summo consensu affirmant Papam posse refringere Dei mandata &amp; dispensare contra Apostolum &amp; in Evangelio. <hi>Peter du Moulin in his novelty of Papisme, l. 1. c. 59. pag. 245. at the title of the Chapter:</hi> The popes have placed their canons above the canonique Scriptures. <hi>The same author in his leter for answer to that of Balzac:</hi> That's well for the Roman Church, in which the Pope doth boast of haveing power to change, that which God has comanded by his word.</note> wee give power to the Pope, to Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the Comandements
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:36398:38"/> of God, to dispence with the Gospell, &amp; against the Apostle, that<note n="(d)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico Orthodoxo, seu summâ Controversiar. tract. 2. quaest 34 §. 2. tom. 1. pag 351.</hi> Papa Papistarum est Idolum. <hi>Petrus Martyr, Locor. Com. class. 2. c. 4. §. 2. pag. 190.</hi> Papistae Idolola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>riam committunt, cùm ita se ad Papae pedes abjiciunt, ut se velle ei subjici testentur, tamquàm unico Christi Vicario in terris. <hi>Vide Hieronymum Zanchium oper. Theologicor. tom 4. pag. 505. Daillé in his Reply to Adam &amp; Cottyby par 2. ch. 6. pag. 46.</hi> you say wee are guilty of Calumnie, for haveing qalified the honnours which the Roman Church gives the Pope with the name of Adoration &amp;c. but our Innocence is so Clear, &amp;c.</note> the Pope is an Idoll, &amp; that wee are Idolaters for obeying him as wee do; that<note n="(e)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>The national Synode of the pretended Reformed held at Gap in 1603.</hi> Since the Bishop of Rome is aspired to name himselfe God, he would be adored, &amp; all power in heaven &amp; Earth atributed unto him, <hi>&amp;c. Thesaurus disput. Sedanens thesi 58. de satisfact, parte. 2. tom. 1. pag. 622.</hi> Papa adoratur adoratione religiosa, &amp; passim in scriptis Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum Romanensium, Deus &amp; majestas divina appellatur.</note> wee adore him with the adoration of latrie which is due onely to God, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leing him God &amp; divine Majestie, that<note n="(f)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Peter du Moulin in Hyperaspiste l. 1. c. 34. pag. 267.</hi> Pontifex Romanus pro suâ sapientiâ procudit novum Evangelium longè praestantius &amp; ad rem faciendam accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datius veteri illo Apostolorum Evangelio, quod in Ecclesia Romana pridem exolevit,</note> the Pope has built a new Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in the place of the old; that<note n="(g)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Joannes Calvinus institut. l. 4. c. 2. §. 12. pag. 281.</hi> Antichristum in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo Dei sessurum praedixerunt Daniel &amp; Paulus; illius scelerati &amp; abominandi regni ducem &amp; Antesignanum apud nos facimus Romanum Pontificem. <hi>Et cap 7. §. 25. pag. 30<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</hi> Videmur nonnullis, nimis maledicè petulantes, cum Romanum Pontificem vocamus Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christum. The Nationall Synode of the Pretended Reformed held at Gap in <hi>1603,</hi> wee believe that the Pope is properly the Antichrist <hi>&amp;c. Guilielmus Amesius Theologiae Doctor in Academia Frankerana in libro cui titulus est</hi> Bellarminus enervatus <hi>tom. 1. cap. 4. pag. 172. Edit. Amstelo lamensis ann. 1630.</hi> Quaestio est, an Pontifex Romanus sit Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chistus ille de quo Apostoli praemonuerunt: Pontisicii negant, nos affirmamus. <hi>Thesaurus disput. Sedanens. tom. 2. pag. 586.</hi> Ejusmodi Pontifex non est Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>arius Christi, aut Ecclesiae caput; sed cauda <hi>Es. 9. v. 14.</hi> Hoc est Propheta mendatium loquem &amp; Antichristus. <hi>Franciscus Burmannus in Synopsi Theolog. l. 8 c. 18 §. 10. pag. 575. tom. 2. Georgius Dounamus in l. cui titulus:</hi> Papa Antichristus: <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>cus Rhonaeus in l. cui titulus</hi> de idea Antichristi raformandi <hi>Du Plesis Mornay in his Mistery of Iniquity. Charles Drelincour Minister of Charenton in his book of the triumph of the Church upon the Cross pag. 29. of the 2. Edition of Geneva 1630.</hi> Almost at the same time that the Pope began to lift up his hornes in the west, Mahomet got up in the east; These Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall Enemies of Iesus-Christ, Gog &amp; Magog.</note> he is Antichrist, &amp; that Mahomet &amp; he
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:36398:39"/> are the Gog &amp; the Magog Cheife Enemies of JESUS-CHRIST, of whom it is spoken in the Scripture; that to have<note n="(h)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Georgius Dounamus in fine praedicti libri</hi> de Papâ Antichristo, <hi>pag. 651. &amp; 652.</hi> Deducitur necessariâ consequentiâ, omnem cum Papa tanquam cum Capite, Romanaque sede Communionem illicitam esse; quae enim Communio Christo cum Belial, hoc est Antichristo &amp;c. <hi>4.</hi> in Christiana Republica benè consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta, non esse tolerandos Antichristi Emissarios, Sacerdotes, Iesuitas &amp;c. <hi>5.</hi> non esse ferendam Papismi, hoc est Antichristianismi professionem.</note> comunion with him, is to associate with Belial, &amp; that in a Republick well polish'd, they ought not to suffer those who profess obedience to the Pope; that<note n="(i)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Francis Bourgoing; Minister of Geneva. l. 2. of his Eclesiastick Historie cap. 5. tom. 1. pag. 229. of the Edition of 1560.</hi> The Pope Institutes &amp; ordains Sacraments at his pleasure he corrupts those instituted by Iesus-Christ, even wholy, abolisheth them, and in their places, he substitutes Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledges, which he himselfe forged.</note> wee give him the power to Institute Sacraments at his pleasure; that<note n="(k)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Franciscus Burmanus in Synopsi Theologica l. 8, c. 18 §. 10. tom. 2. pag. 576.</hi> Vt autem verum &amp; indubitatum Antichristum se proderet, omnia Christi munera invasit; Propheticum puta per substitutionem novi verbi <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>; Sacerdotale per introductionem novi sacrificii &amp; intercessorum praeter Christum; Regium per dominium in conscientias, &amp; imperium in vivos, non solum; sed &amp; mortuos.</note> to leave no doubt of his being Antichrist, he has invaded &amp; vsurped all the Rights of JESUS-CHRIST; that of Prophesie, by substituteing a new word not written in the place of the Gospell; that of the Preisthood by introduceing a new sacrifice, &amp; intercessors with God besides JESUS-CHRIST; that of the Royalty, by atributeing to him, the domination of Consciences, &amp; the power to Comand over the liveing &amp; the dead, that<note n="(l)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico ortodoxo seu summâ Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. tract. 2. q. 5. §. 7. tom. 1. pag. 326</hi> Non solum vita, sed etiam doctrina consequens, titulique à Papa usurpati, satis ostendunt ipsum esse Christi hostem, Christumque negare, ut Epicurus providentiam destruens, Deum negabat. Hoc à nobis demonstratum fuit.</note> not onely the life of the Pope, but also his Doctrine, &amp; the titles of honnour which he atri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes to himselfe, makes it clear, that he is the Enemie of JESUS-CHRIST, &amp; that he believes in JESUS-CHRIST no more then Epicure did in God when he denied his Providence; that<note n="(m)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Franciscus Burmanus l. 8. c. 18. §, 9. tom. 2. pag. 575.</hi> Papismus ex ludaismo &amp; Ethnicismo conflatus, &amp; utrumque nefario Religionis adulterio cum Christianissimo commiscens. Ab Ethnicis enim ritus, idololatriam, &amp; superstitionem; à Iudais ritus quoque &amp; pedagogiam veteris testamenti mutuantes Pontifices, utramque Christiano nomine &amp; habitu tinxerunt &amp; circumvestierunt, quas tres Religiones Hierarchiae vinculo colligatas exhibet Papismus</note> Papisme is a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion composed of Paganisme &amp; Judaisme, mixt together by an adultera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Alliance; that<note n="(n)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Andraeas Rivetus in Catholico ortodoxo seu summa Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. q. 1. Prooemiali de Haeresibus tom. 1 pag. 42.</hi> Liquet appositissime quosdam Papismum comparasse mari mango, in quod que madmodum flumina omnia &amp; rivi decidunt pleno alveo; sic etiam plurimae &amp; pene omnes variorum temporum, locorum &amp; personarum haereses in hunc errorum abyssum fluunt, &amp; impuris ejus undis miscentur.</note> Papisme is most Justly compared to a great sea, because it comprehends almost all sorts of heresies that ever was, as the sea Doth the Rivers; that Papisme is as far from Christianisme, as<note n="(o)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Theodorus Beza in Antithesi Papatus &amp; Christianismi tractar. theologic. tom. 1. pag. 56.</hi> Hoc affirmo, atque utinam non possem tamjustis de causi affirmare, album nigro non magis repugnare, quàm Papismum Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nismo.</note> black is from white; that<note n="(p)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Peter du Moulin in his letter for answer to that of Balzac:</hi> From thence it comes that all things are sold in the Church of Rome, even God himselfe &amp; the Remission of sins.</note> in the Church of Rome every thing is sold, God himselfe, &amp; the Remission of sinns; finally, that<note n="(q)" place="bottom">
                              <hi>Idem Theodorus Beza loco mox laudato:</hi> jugulum causae peto, doctrinam illorum nimirum, quâ nihil impurius &amp; corruptius, ne fingi quidem posse affirmo.</note> 'tis impossible to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a Doctrine more Impure &amp; more Corrupted, then that of the Church.</p>
                     </div>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:36398:39"/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="approbation">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:36398:40"/>
                     <p>Read &amp; approved in the General Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Clergie of France held at Saint Germains in Laye, by permission of the King, on wednesday the 11th of July &amp; signed on saturday the 14th of same Month 1685. By the Clergie before named from pag. 14. to. pag. 16.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="edict">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:36398:40"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE EDICT OF THE KING,</hi> Which defends the Ministers &amp; all others of the P. R. R. to Preach, or compose books, stuff'd vvith lies and Calumnies against the Doctrine of the Church, nor to make use of termes tending to Calumnie, by imputeing Doctrines to Catholicks, vvhich they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>OUIS BY THE GRACE OF GOD, OF FRANCE AND NAVARRE KING; To all present &amp; to come, GREETING. The deputed of the Clergie of our kingdome by our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mision assembled at our Citty of Saint Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in Laye, haveing Represented unto us, that amongst other means, of which the Ministers of the P. R. R. do make use, to hinder the conversion of divers of our subjects who make profession of that Religion, there is none suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds with so much success as that of giveing by impostures a false Idea of the Catholick Religion to the people; &amp; haveing humbly pray'd us at the same time to prevent the continuation of so great an Evill, by such means as wee should thinck most convenient; wee have Examin'd the errors which the Ministers &amp; others of the P. R. R. do impute to the Catholick Religion in their sermons &amp; books. Which they compose, &amp; as nothing so much wounds the Respect, with which our Edicts oblidges them to speak of the Catholick Religion, as to accuse our Church of professing a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:36398:41"/> which she Condemns, &amp; that it is not just to suffer that their Calumnies should infuse into our subjects à horrour of the truth, which they could not but love &amp; follow if they were not deprived of the knowledge therof by such deceitfull means; &amp; haveing otherwise consider'd, that it ought to suffice the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of à Religion onely tollerated in our kingdome by the Edicts of the kings our predecessors &amp; by our one, to teach their doctrine, without somenting Callumnies against the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of which wee make profession, &amp; from which their prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors did in the last age unhappily seperate: wee therfore have thought it necessarie to put à stop to the course of such à liberty, which has produced such dreadfull Effects. MAKEING KNOWNE, that for these and other causes us therunto moveing, &amp; of our Certaine knowledge, full power &amp; Royall authority, wee have by this present Edict defended &amp; do hearby defend all Ministers &amp; others of what quality or Condition soever they be, professing the Pretended Reformed Religion, to Preach or compose any books against the faith &amp; Doctrine of the holy Catholick, Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick &amp; Roman Religion; or to supply themselves with Injurious termes tending to Callumnie, by imputeing Doctrines to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks which they condemn, or to speak directly or indirectly without Respect in any maner whatever of the Catholick Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wee enjoyne the Ministers to teach in their sermons only the Doctrine of the pretended Reformed Religion, &amp; the rules of Morality, without touching any thing elss. Wee further forbid the Ministers, &amp; all others our subjects who make profession of the said P. R. R. to cause to be printed any book or books concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Religion, except such as conteine their profession of faith their prayers &amp; the ordinarie rules of their discipline, &amp; to all Printers &amp; book sellers to print or sell them: wee will, that all such books as have been made to this houre against the Catholick Religion by those of the P. R. R. be supprest, wee forbid all prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to print them &amp; all stationers to sell them for the future. Wee will &amp; comand that the Ministers &amp; our other subjects, of the P. R. R. who shall transgress against this our present Edict,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:36398:41"/> be condemn'd to pay an honourable fine, &amp; for ever Banished out of our kingdome, &amp; their goods subject to Confiscation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiscated, &amp; the Excercise of that Religion forever prohibited in those places where the Ministers shall preach against the intent of this our present Edict. Wee will likewise that all printers &amp; Book-sellers, who shall print or sell the said books to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of this present Edict, be condemn'd to pay 1500. Livres fine &amp; forever made uncapable to keep open shop. So GIVEING BY COMAND to our beloued &amp; Loyall subjects, holding our court of Parliament at Paris, that they cause this present Edict to be read, published &amp; Registred, &amp; the contents therin contein'd, to keep &amp; observe according its forme &amp; tenour, without trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressing or suffering the same to be transgressed in any sorte or manner whatsoever, for such is our will &amp; pleasure, &amp; to the end it may be made firme and stable for ever, wee have caused our seal to be put to these presents. GIUEN at Versailles in the month of August, &amp; year of grace one thousand six hundred Eighty five, &amp; of our Reigne the three &amp; fortieth. Signed LOUIS. &amp; upon the fold: By the King, Colbert, &amp; sealed with the great seale of green wax, on labels of Red &amp; green silk.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="approbation">
                  <head>APPROBATIO.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>UM nihil sit in omnibus rerum humanarum negotiis cuivis homini, de Salute suâ vel mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum soliciti, antiquiùs, quam ut de Religione sua fiat certior; nihil est etiam publico commodo necessarium magis, quam de Religione pro com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni bono libros componere, ut verá à falsis Secretâ &amp; notâ, Beatitudinis extremae spes in tuto posita sit. Hoc multis ab annis clerum Gallicanum occupare nemo est qui nesciat; &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:36398:42"/> in his novissimis temporibus quisque potest experiri, quid, horum comitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quae invictissimo Galliarum Rege LUDOVICO XIV. convocante &amp; protegente, pro rerum Ecclesiaticorum restauratione celebrantur, zelus, Scientia, pietas &amp; sufficientia valeant. Regna mirantur, &amp; obstupes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt vniversi fines terrae, cum eis annuntiatur Galliae fides. Celebrari igitur debet omnibus linguis illa natio, per quam diffamatur, ut ait Apostolus, sermo Domini, nec ullo idiomate non dicendum, quid his temporibus, pro extirpandis haeresibus foeliciter susceperit, &amp; foelicius absolverit. Fecit hoc, qui fideliter Anglis idiomate Britannico, postrema Galliae comitiorum acta transtulit de Gallico, quorum titulum sic exprimi vidimus <hi>The proceedings of the Generall assembly of the Clergie of France.</hi> Vix pro nostro tenui hujus linguae usu de hac traductione ferre judicium arbitrabamur, sed adducto in dubiis, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num hac in reperitorum, &amp; ex Angliâ oriundorum, judicio, nobis prorsus fuit satisfactum, &amp; in hoc libro nihil invenimus, quod ortodoxae fidei, &amp; Originali non Concordaret. Datum Insulis die Februarij <hi>28.</hi> anni <hi>1686.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>F. DESQUEUX</hi> Pastor S. Stephani Decanus Christianitatis Insulensis Librorum Censor.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="approbation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>PERMISSION,</hi> De Monseigneur DUGUE' DE BAGNOLS Conseiller du Roy en son Conseil d'Estat, Maistre des Requestes ordinaire de son Hostel, Intendant de la Justice, Police &amp; Finances en Flandres.</head>
                  <p>VEu l'Approbation, permis d'imprimer. Fait à Lille le 9. Mars 1686.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>DUGUE' DE BAGNOLS.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:36398:42"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>